<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>St. Cecily, or, The converted twins a Christian tragedy / written by E.M.</title>
            <author>Medbourne, M. (Matthew), d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1583B</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12561072</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12561072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199600)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 768:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>St. Cecily, or, The converted twins a Christian tragedy / written by E.M.</title>
                  <author>Medbourne, M. (Matthew), d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Streater,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>"Never before published."</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Matthew Medbourne. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Forster Collection, Victoria and Albert Museum.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> CECILY: OR, The Converted Twins.</p>
            <p>A Chriſtian Tragedy.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>E. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Never before Publiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license_to_print">
                        <p>Licenſed,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>
                              <hi>June</hi> 11. 1666.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Streater,</hi> M.DC.LXVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:199600:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199600:2"/>
            <head>To Her Sacred MAJESTY, THE QUEEN-Conſort.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAME,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is ſo great a diſtance between the <hi>Meanneſs</hi> of a Comedian, and the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of a Crown'd Head, that the preſumption of this Addreſs may occaſion ſome, to charge me with an Oblivion of the former, and want of reverence to the Sacredneſſe of the latter. 'Tis true, at the firſt bluſh, it might appear ſo; but I have this ſelf-encouragement, that my applications are made to a <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> ſurrounded with <hi>Goodneſſe;</hi> to an equal tranſcendency of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Piety:</hi> and <hi>Theſe</hi> regard not ſo much the <hi>Merit,</hi> as the <hi>Humility</hi> of the Supplyant.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>MADAME,</hi> when I finde repreſented in this ſmall Piece, the <hi>Triumphs</hi> of <hi>Divine Love</hi> over all the moſt alluring Concerns of Sublunary Happineſſe; When I reflect on a tender <hi>Virginity,</hi> defying all the charming enjoyments of this World, nay what's moſt harſh to the delicacy of that fair ſex, <hi>Torture;</hi> When I ſee enflam'd Youth, by an Heroick contempt, ſpurning the greateſt Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, to court the Croſs of Chriſt: When I obſerve the
<pb facs="tcp:199600:3"/>ſudden, yet efficacious Operations of that <hi>Winde which bloweth where it liſteth,</hi> converting a <hi>Saul</hi> into a <hi>Paul,</hi> a Perſecutor into a Sufferer: And laſtly, when I conſider, how the want of an humble <hi>Perſeverance</hi> (like an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Wrack within the Port) made way to the <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> of one ready to lay hold on the Crown of <hi>Martyrdom:</hi> When theſe Reflexions fill my thoughts, how ſhould I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any <hi>Patronage</hi> too great for ſo great <hi>Examples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, <hi>MADAME,</hi> were the Inducements pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd with me, to offer them to that of your Sacred Majeſty: For, where ſhould <hi>Innocency, Vertue, Piety,</hi> and all the other amazing heights of Chriſtian life, expect to be more kindly <hi>entertain'd,</hi> than where they are in the higheſt degree <hi>practis'd?</hi> Whileſt then they are admitted into ſo Royall a Preſence, if I can but preſs in, as the meaneſt Attendant, after ſo Noble a <hi>Train,</hi> it will be only with this hope, that Your Majeſty may, though at a great diſtance ſhed ſome providential Graces upon,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAME,</salute>
               <signed>Your Majeſties moſt dutifull and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>M. MEDBVRNE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:199600:3"/>
            <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CECILIE</hi> Daughter of <hi>Marcus</hi> and <hi>Flavia,</hi> was a young Virgin, beautiful, well deſcended, and, though ſhe had ſecretly <hi>vow'd Virginity,</hi> yet out of compliance with the diſpoſal of her parents, married to a Nobleman of <hi>Rome,</hi> named <hi>Valerian,</hi> then a Worſhipper of Idols, but afterward by her perſwaded to embrace the <hi>Chriſtian' Faith:</hi> That done, they both joyn their endeavours for the <hi>Converſion</hi> of <hi>Tiburtius,</hi> Younger Brother to <hi>Valerian,</hi> and his <hi>Corrival;</hi> and theſe alſo prov'd effectual.</p>
            <p>The two <hi>Brothers,</hi> having declar'd themſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> were by the Praetor <hi>Almachius</hi> condemn'd to <hi>die,</hi> which Sentence being firſt executed on <hi>Tiburtius,</hi> occaſion'd his precedence in the <hi>Martyrology,</hi> before his Elder Brother <hi>Valerian. Maximus</hi> (the Principal Officer appointed to ſee this Execution) rendring <hi>Almachius</hi> an account of it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verrs, that he had ſeen their ſouls convey'd to heaven by two bright Angels: which acknowledgement inducing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers preſent to profeſs Chriſtianity, <hi>Maximus</hi> is beaten to death with Staves, having Plummets of Lead faſten'd to the ends of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cecilie,</hi> the Worker of all theſe Enchauntments as they thought, is for theſe Crimes, eſpecially her debauching the <hi>Two Brothers</hi> from the ſervice of the gods, condemn'd to the flames, and to that end diſpos'd into a dry Bath ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with fire; but that not approaching her body in the ſpace of a Day and Night, order was given for her <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heading.</hi> In that Execution, after ſhe had receiv'd three blows, which ſeem'd to have ſever'd her head from her <pb facs="tcp:199600:4"/>body, ſhe liv'd three dayes, during which, ſhe gain'd her Parents, and made this her laſt requeſt, that the Houſe, wherein ſhe had liv'd, might be converted into a Church, which it was, and afterward conſecrated by Biſhop <hi>URBAN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any be deſirous of a more particular Information con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the perſons before mentioned, as alſo of the ſtrange and remarkable accident, which happen'd between <hi>Saphri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> they may conſult the Writers of <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> who have given an account of them. But thoſe being not ſo obvious, they may ſhorten their ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by looking into the <hi>Collection of Saints Lives,</hi> ſet out by ſome late <hi>Authors</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> wherein they ſhall find thoſe of <hi>Tiburtius, Valerian, Maximus, &amp;c.</hi> on the 14th. day of <hi>April;</hi> and that of St. <hi>Cecilie</hi> on the 22th. of <hi>November,</hi> in the year of our Lord <hi>CCXXV.</hi> in the <hi>Perſecution</hi> under the Emperour <hi>Alexander Severus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:199600:4"/>
            <head>To his ingenious and learned Friends, the Author and Publiſher of this Chriſtian Tragedy.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IT is the cuſtome of this brainſick Age,</l>
               <l>To boaſt with boldneſs and fanatick Rage,</l>
               <l>An imitation of that Doctrine pure,</l>
               <l>For which the Primitive Chriſtians did endure</l>
               <l>Afflictions, Torments, nay the loſſe of life;</l>
               <l>Each vying in a holy Zeal and Strife</l>
               <l>t'outgo the other; but if once it come</l>
               <l>To feel the Perſecutions, that in <hi>Rome</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Firſt <hi>Catechumens</hi> ſuffred; ſtraight they cry</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quis requiſivit,</hi> ſuch <hi>Hyperbole</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of Faith, as ſhould produce in any one</l>
               <l>Such Works of <hi>Supererogation?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Alas! Weak <hi>Fondlings,</hi> it is not enough</l>
               <l>To cloak <hi>Religion</hi> with new-fangled ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>And then cry out <hi>Antiquity!</hi> You muſt</l>
               <l>Believe and honour the <hi>Old Martyrs</hi> duſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>True Religion</hi> beſt agree,</l>
               <l>As Diſcords make compleateſt Harmony.</l>
               <l>Happy the ſtrain of your ingenious <hi>Pen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That doth refreſh the memory agen.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Pious Martyrs,</hi> and Thy labour too</l>
               <l>For publiſhing the ſame, deſerves its due,</l>
               <l>Which ſhall be this, ſtill to preſerve your Name</l>
               <l>To equal date with St. <hi>Cecilia's</hi> Fame:</l>
               <l>Who living did in <hi>Vertue</hi> ſo excel,</l>
               <l>That even her <hi>Death</hi> became a <hi>Miracle.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And if hereafter you no more ſhall do,</l>
               <l>To ſecond this, yet we will boaſt, that you</l>
               <l>Have ſo to life the <hi>Martyrs</hi> drawn herein,</l>
               <l>As would invite a <hi>Heathen</hi> to begin.</l>
               <l>To live and do, and then like them to die,</l>
               <l>Inroll'd ith' Records of <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ceaſe then, vain <hi>World,</hi> to rail againſt a <hi>Play,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since this ſhews pure <hi>Religion;</hi> If you ſay.</l>
               <l>Therefore it is <hi>Prophane,</hi> change but the <hi>Name</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Call it a <hi>Sermon,</hi> and it is the ſame,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Uſe</hi> and <hi>Doctrine</hi> too; and ſince you make</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Religion</hi> ſo much <hi>Droll,</hi> ne're ſhame to take.</l>
               <l>From hence a <hi>Pattern,</hi> better than have none:</l>
               <l>By <hi>Acting</hi> ſeem to have <hi>Religion.</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. M. Med. Tem. Soc.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:199600:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>WEre I the <hi>Author,</hi> had an <hi>Angel's Pen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I think, I ſcarce ſhould ever write agen;</l>
               <l>Unleſſe the <hi>Criticks</hi> will <hi>contract</hi> and <hi>ſwear</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They'l out of <hi>pity</hi> pardon me <hi>this Year;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And give me leave freely to <hi>vend</hi> a <hi>Book</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I hazarded to <hi>print,</hi> which ſeem'd forſook,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the <hi>Author</hi> had no <hi>Name</hi> that might</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conjure</hi> and <hi>charm</hi> the <hi>Reader</hi> at firſt ſight.</l>
               <l>As 'tis with <hi>Stationers,</hi> ſo with the <hi>Theatre</hi> too,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Author</hi> muſt be <hi>famous,</hi> elſe 'two'nt do.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſtay — what need I fear the <hi>Criticks</hi> ſpite?</l>
               <l>While they are ignorant, who it is do's <hi>write,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They neither know whom to <hi>condemn</hi> nor <hi>praiſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But if they did, his <hi>Vertue</hi> has <hi>Allays,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That can <hi>diſpence</hi> with either <hi>paſſion,</hi> and</l>
               <l>Submit his <hi>Judgement,</hi> and with-hold his <hi>hand.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <head>Drammatis Perſonae.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Valerian <hi>Twins and Noblemen of</hi> Rome.</item>
               <item>Tiburtius <hi>Twins and Noblemen of</hi> Rome.</item>
               <item>Marcus <hi>Father and Mother to</hi> Cecilie.</item>
               <item>Flavia <hi>Father and Mother to</hi> Cecilie.</item>
               <item>Cecilie, <hi>their Daughter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Anguſta, <hi>her Waiting-Woman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Metricio, <hi>her Poet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Phantaſio, <hi>her Muſitian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Palinodio <hi>her Gentleman-Uſher.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Turcius Almachius, <hi>a Judge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Maximus, <hi>his chief Officer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Saphricius, <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nicephorus, <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Urbanus, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rome.</item>
               <item>Angel.</item>
               <item>Devil.</item>
               <item>Headſman.</item>
               <item>Officers.</item>
               <item>Watchmen.</item>
               <item>Attendants.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199600:5"/>
            <head>St. CECILIE, OR, The Converted Tvvins.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACTUS I.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> TIBURTIUS SOLUS.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Younger Brother, — true; I am but ſo;</l>
                  <l>Yet younger is comparative: why then,</l>
                  <l>I may compare in blood, in worth, in all,</l>
                  <l>But that of time, when the ſurrounding Sun,</l>
                  <l>Rides Circuit in his Sphere. And what are dayes?</l>
                  <l>But ever-dying Brothers hatcht by light,</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Sol</hi> turns Retrograde? and then good night.—</l>
                  <l>But now 'tis morn, to which I open firſt,</l>
                  <l>A pair of Chryſtals: And in this reſpect,</l>
                  <l>While yet <hi>Valerian</hi> ſleeps, I ſeem to be</l>
                  <l>The Elder Brother; Say, he did out-ſtrip</l>
                  <l>Me once, an hour, or ſuch a matter, when</l>
                  <l>We twins were bedding in one darkſome room,</l>
                  <l>Where firſt he wak'd; and from the tyring houſe,</l>
                  <l>(The Wombe,) came to the Stage of this vaſt world,</l>
                  <l>To act the mournfull, ſilly Babe, and cry.</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:199600:6"/>
                  <l>Yet now, as not ſurviving, he, nor eats,</l>
                  <l>Nor drinks, nor hears, nor underſtands ſo much</l>
                  <l>As that he lives; have I not (then) gain'd hours</l>
                  <l>Of him that ſleeps? May ſeem the elder brother;</l>
                  <l>At leaſt in one precedence, if the light</l>
                  <l>His miſtris darts, illuſtrates firſt my ſight.—</l>
                  <l>This is the houſe; the Pallace might have ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Where Lady <hi>Cecilie</hi> the fair is lodg'd.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Valerian.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>It were too great a happineſs to ſee</l>
                  <l>But thoſe her brighter Starres. But ah too ſoon</l>
                  <l>My Brother's here. Suſpition is a reſtleſs</l>
                  <l>Inmate; and Jealouſie too ſwift of wing,</l>
                  <l>Will not permit a Rival in his Love.—</l>
                  <l>The goodly ſtructure here I muſt admire,</l>
                  <l>And not the Beauty that's contain'd within,</l>
                  <l>Gaze on the Cabinet not view the Gemme.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Good morrow Brother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>The gods give you as much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are wondrous godly grown of late: as if</l>
                  <l>Heaven were your Book; or turn'd Aſtronomer</l>
                  <l>Were rapt in Contemplation, viewing-how,</l>
                  <l>With equal meaſure in the Azure plain,</l>
                  <l>Each Conſtellation, keeps his courſe, and round.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis even ſo. But when I lower ſtoop,</l>
                  <l>My greedy ear, from you bright Caſement, charm'd;</l>
                  <l>Would hear thoſe ſweeter ſtrains of harmony;</l>
                  <l>To raviſh my dull ſoul with Admiration.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>No more: of that. Be <hi>Uranoſcopos;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Fiſh whoſe goggle-eyes, fixt on his Crown,</l>
                  <l>Is gazing on the ſtarry ſpangled skie.</l>
                  <l>So you— ſtoop not t'an earthly Deity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <l>Mark but the ſway an Elder brother bears.—</l>
                  <l>Sir, when <hi>Gemini</hi> predominate, they ſay,</l>
                  <l>The heats are doubled. You and I were twins;</l>
                  <l>May then participate in Love; as well</l>
                  <l>As heretofore in life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Know your Devoir.</l>
                  <l>And let the Nonage, though but of an hour—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Make you know your ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <l>To be your Brother.—</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199600:6"/>
                  <l>We hadbut one Horoſcopus: but one</l>
                  <l>Aſcendent in Nativity. If under</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> you were born, why not I? or elſe —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>What elſe, but that you are impertinent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>Elſe <hi>Mars</hi> became my Zenith, and not yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet I can wield a Sword.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>And I dare fight.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Palinodio <hi>in huſte.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Gentlemen, or Lords, or whatſo'ere you be,</l>
                  <l>I muſt be bold to interrupt you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>Crave but a period to your loud diſcourſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Speak that agen, and—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, ſpeak your pleaſures,</l>
                  <l>Gentlemen; and if your voyce be conſonant</l>
                  <l>To what you promiſe outwardly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are worthy Gentlemen. Yet I could wiſh</l>
                  <l>A moderation of your Dialect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhy, what art thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>My Name may intimate,</l>
                  <l>That I am courteous, and reſpectful too,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Palinodio;</hi> not to cant, but to recan,</l>
                  <l>If I tranſgreſs beyond the precincts, of</l>
                  <l>A Gentleman Uſher.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>To whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Unto no leſs, than to the vertuous,</l>
                  <l>And moſt incomparable Lady, <hi>Cecilie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVho 'bove th' Horizon of this Earthly Ball,</l>
                  <l>Rais'd to the ſervice of th' immortal power,</l>
                  <l>Each day outſtrips <hi>Aurora,</hi> in her courſe.</l>
                  <l>And cauſe ſhe's now within her Oratory,</l>
                  <l>It is my duty to divert from hence,</l>
                  <l>Th' obſtrepercus.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>The obſtreperous?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Not you,</l>
                  <l>Gentlemen; but ſuch as are her ſervants.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Such am I, and thouſands mo, my Attendants.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>VVe have no employment, Sir, for ſo many.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>They are my thoughts, which from an endleſs ſource</l>
                  <l>Spring up, and like a ſwelling torrent flow,</l>
                  <l>To reſt in her, and find a ſweet repoſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199600:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Reſt, and repoſe! if you knew how wakeful</l>
                  <l>She is, and how ſhe watches night by night,</l>
                  <l>You'd ſeek repoſe elſewhere. That Sir, is the</l>
                  <l>Short, I cannot ſay the long of the buſineſs:</l>
                  <l>For her ſleeps go, but by ſnatches, like pocket</l>
                  <l>Purſe raptures; ſnap and away. Witneſs here.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Anguſta <hi>yawning,</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>My Ladies Woman, Mrs. <hi>Anguſta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By Name, who by watching is as you ſee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang. Au-guſta. Au-guſta!</speaker>
                  <p>who calls me there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh! the ambition of a waiting woman!</l>
                  <l>Who even yawning, gapeth after honour.</l>
                  <l>Her Name's <hi>Anguſta,</hi> rather <hi>Anguſtula.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang. Au-guſta!</speaker>
                  <p>Do's any body call me there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>Marry that do I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Marry that, marry piſh!</l>
                  <l>Marry ſuch a Skipjack Gentlemen Uſher!</l>
                  <l>No I warrant you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Warrant me Goſſip!</l>
                  <l>I am warranted, by a vertuous Lady,</l>
                  <l>To be an obſervant, vigilant, and —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>A malapert, impertinent, extravagant</l>
                  <l>Gentleman-Uſher. Marry thee! <hi>Au-guſta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh what greatneſs ſhe yawnes! gapes barn-wide,</l>
                  <l>To ſtrike in at laſt, with a thread-bare ſerving creature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Gentlemen, or Lords, pardon my exorbitance.</l>
                  <l>I know not your occaſions; but this ſhadow</l>
                  <l>Of man, had ſo diſtracted my better thoughts,</l>
                  <l>That, till now, they were not ſo obſervant</l>
                  <l>As the quality of your perſonages,</l>
                  <l>Might more than exact, of your humbleſt ſervant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>So: now ſhe begins to collogue to ſome purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſeems, you are both ſervants to one Lady?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>He, as a Cipher; I a digit, I</l>
                  <l>In her Bed-chamber; from thence, he as remote</l>
                  <l>As our <hi>Alpes,</hi> from the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Mountains.</l>
                  <l>My Lady is a chaſt Lady, lives reſerv'd;</l>
                  <l>Follows not the vogue of our vainer times.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet if you have a priviledge 'bove the reſt,</l>
                  <l>May we not by your powerful privacy,</l>
                  <l>Come to the Speech —</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:199600:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>What of my Lady, Sir?</l>
                  <l>No, but if I lend your eyes an happineſs</l>
                  <l>To ſee, and hear her ſing, will't not ſuffice</l>
                  <l>For the firſt time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt abundantly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Next time, the wakeful clock ſhall notice give,</l>
                  <l>(Her cuſtomary time of prayer expir'd,)</l>
                  <l>She on her Organ plays; to which ſhe addes,</l>
                  <l>The heavenly rapture, of harmonious accents.
<stage>Clock ſtrikes.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hark now it ſtrikes. Gentlemen come near; I dare</l>
                  <l>Contract the Curtain, that the ecchoing Air,</l>
                  <l>May uſher to the heavens, her ſweeter voice;</l>
                  <l>And that you may, be confident I have,</l>
                  <l>A free recourſe unto her private Chamber,</l>
                  <l>Behold a Sonnet! not compos'd by her,</l>
                  <l>But by <hi>Metricio,</hi> her ingenious Poet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>I there goes the Hare away: a petulant</l>
                  <l>Poet, to make her Anagrams, is ſtil'd</l>
                  <l>Ingenious. I ſhall remember this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>I think ſhe now will ſing it; with your favour,</l>
                  <l>I'll read, that you may reliſh it the better:</l>
                  <l>Our Poet tells me I have a ſpecial grace,</l>
                  <l>In the rehearſal; ſeldom coincident</l>
                  <l>To thoſe of our Sex. Which when my Lady chaunts,</l>
                  <l>Souls may be raviſht, 'bove <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> height.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Reads the Song.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If each hive, of ſwarming bees,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Have a King, that careful ſees,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To the Manage: and more ſage,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Keeps the reſt, in vaſſalage:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If each flock, of tender ſheep,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Have a Swain, to feed and keep</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From the Wolf, that ſeeks his prey:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or if onely one muſt ſway;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In a Kingdome: needs muſt gods,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(Powers divided:) live at odds. —</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then Bees, Sheep, and Subjects, we,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Can but have, one Deity.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pack yee hence, you many Gods.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Powers divided, live at odds.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199600:8"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Hum! She contemns the gods.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>And goddeſſes:</l>
                  <l>Why ſhe her ſelf, may compare with <hi>Venus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Beauty; with <hi>Minerva</hi> for Wiſdom:</l>
                  <l>But not with Cuckold <hi>Juno,</hi> for Malice,</l>
                  <l>Towards <hi>Aeneas</hi> that noble progenitor</l>
                  <l>Of our <hi>Roman</hi> Worthies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <l>Can ſhe be vertuous,</l>
                  <l>That ſo neglects, our more immortal Gods?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and as far tranſcending your chaſt <hi>Veſta's,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In purity; as fulgent ſtars of heaven,</l>
                  <l>Shine brighter, than a foggy <hi>Ignis fatuus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Howſoever, let's hear her voice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor that.</l>
                  <l>Nay if you vilifie her worth: or but</l>
                  <l>Extenuate this favour; you ſee your way.
<stage>Points to the Door. Gives her gold. Cecile tunes the Organ within.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, this will qualifie your riſing ſpleen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay now I ſee ſhee'll be <hi>Auguſta.</hi> 'Tis</l>
                  <l>But placing the <hi>N</hi> with the heels upwards.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Gentlemen, She's tuning. Pray make a quick retreat.</l>
                  <l>To ſee and not be ſeen, hear not be heard. —</l>
                  <l>Now; after her more ſweet melodious ſtrains,</l>
                  <l>Her cuſtom is, to walk a while abroad,</l>
                  <l>Not far from hence; take th' opportunity.</l>
                  <l>But ſhould ſhe know I had a hand in this</l>
                  <l>Your interview, I were undone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Fear not.
<stage>Exeunt Valerian &amp; Tiburtius.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Palinodio</hi> let's be gone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Begone, not I.</l>
                  <l>My Lady ſhall know all, or let me have half,</l>
                  <l>Was given thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then my Lady ſhall know</l>
                  <l>What you did Sir, the laſt night</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Kiſſed me.</l>
                  <l>Y'had been better to have kiſs'd elſewhere.</l>
                  <l>Nay, what you would have done beſides, you know;</l>
                  <l>And ſhe ſhall know.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>What then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>What then?</l>
                  <l>You know full well how ſhe abhors ſuch doings.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:199600:8"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>And know your predeceſſor, was tranſplanted</l>
                  <l>For like offence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>And why I pray tranſplanted?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes ſo I ſay, for a Gentleman Uſher,</l>
                  <l>May well be liken'd to a double Gilliflower,</l>
                  <l>Which while it ſo continues, is eſteem'd;</l>
                  <l>And ſo is he, with two good ſuits of clothes:</l>
                  <l>But let him wear out one, and be but ſingle,</l>
                  <l>In a thread-bare ſuit, he's ſoon tranſplanted,</l>
                  <l>As ſingle Gilliflowers, are wont to be:</l>
                  <l>His Lady then cries up, and out with him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>This is a parlous wench, how ſhe threatens me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mum</hi> then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>I, <hi>Mum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>See then you tell no-body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>Not I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis well you ſing a <hi>Palinodie.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Come Sir, know your duty, and attend upon me.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Valerian <hi>&amp;</hi> Tiburtius <hi>liſtning to St.</hi> Cecilie, <hi>that ſings to the Organ within, then comes forth, and ſpying</hi> Valerian and Tiburtius <hi>ſtarts.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <l>Bleſſe me! where was my Porter? where my ſervants?</l>
                  <l>Who has betrayed me to the ſight of men?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Of Men, Lady? whom would you ſee but Man?</l>
                  <l>The Maſter-piece of th' Earth, who joys to ſee</l>
                  <l>His like in her who is a ſecond ſelf?</l>
                  <l>What creature to be parallell'd with man,</l>
                  <l>Can you behold? why then ſhould palid fear</l>
                  <l>Undie thoſe roſie cheeks, and coral lips?</l>
                  <l>You need not fear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, like the trembling tree,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe every leaf, ſhakes at th' approach of man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>We'll not offend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <l>But chaſtity is ſuch,</l>
                  <l>It cannot be too wary; fear too much.
<stage>She offers to go out, but courteouſly returns.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay Lady, leave us not ſo abruptly.</l>
                  <l>I would, but dare not ſay, at firſt, I love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bec.</speaker>
                  <l>Not love? you told me you were men; not love?</l>
                  <l>Why 'tis the nobleſt paſſion of the ſoul;</l>
                  <l>Sprung from the Will, which cannot love, but good.</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:199600:9"/>
                  <l>Much more the greateſt good, whoſe only Beauty,</l>
                  <l>Is ſo attractive, that when 'tis but known,</l>
                  <l>It cannot be, but lov'd: Ah Noble Sir,</l>
                  <l>Dare you not love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Not you Lady, I mean,</l>
                  <l>I durſt not ſay I lov'd: but know I do.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah! There's ſmall difference 'twixt wo and woe.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tiburtius,</hi> here's a ſpark, what's thy opinion</l>
                  <l>Of this Lady?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <l>That ſhe's like other females,</l>
                  <l>Who know themſelves, to be the weaker veſſels;</l>
                  <l>Like melting wax that's apt for all impreſſions</l>
                  <l>At firſt encounter; therefore by retreat,</l>
                  <l>(Fearing they ſhould be almoſt gain'd, ere courted,</l>
                  <l>(Which they affect:) they ſuddenly with-draw;</l>
                  <l>The better to attract: for after that, we fly,</l>
                  <l>Which flies from us; neglect, what is atchiev'd:</l>
                  <l>And what is fair, muſt hardly be obtain'd,</l>
                  <l>By frequent ſuits; which they affect, as a</l>
                  <l>Supream honour, and homage due, to their</l>
                  <l>Self-ſeeming, pretious, and admir'd beauties.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>This is not all I fear, for I obſerv'd,</l>
                  <l>Both in her Sonnet, and her Maids diſcourſe,</l>
                  <l>A kind of Superſtition, mixt with a</l>
                  <l>Contempt, of all our gods. If that impoſture</l>
                  <l>Of Chriſtianiſme, has infected her,</l>
                  <l>I fear twill be a Bar to my deſignes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <l>Tuſh! Take no notice what ſhe young of years,</l>
                  <l>Has yet but ſuckt, not turn'd to nutriment. —</l>
                  <l>Love ſoon extirpates what's but newly ſet.</l>
                  <l>And taking deeper root, predominates,</l>
                  <l>O're all the powers of man; and that we call</l>
                  <l>Religion; but a trifle; and ſubordinate,</l>
                  <l>To Love's tranſcendent paſſion of the Soul.</l>
                  <l>Our gods themſelves, vanquiſh'd by powerful Love,</l>
                  <l>Have laid aſide their Deities to court</l>
                  <l>A Beauty. Shall not then Religion,</l>
                  <l>Which but relates, unto thoſe heavenly powers,</l>
                  <l>Subſcribe unto the Soveraignty of Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Heavens grant it may, but ſoft, whoſe coming here?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199600:9"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Marcus <hi>and</hi> Flavia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Come <hi>Flavia,</hi> my dear ſweet wife; where's our daughter,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cecilie;</speaker>
                  <l>the fooliſh Girle is ſo penſive</l>
                  <l>And ſolitary: Shees never well; but when</l>
                  <l>She's in her Chamber. This dull Melancholy, caus'd</l>
                  <l>By her too much delight in Muſick, has brought her</l>
                  <l>To that paſſe for want of exerciſe (poor elfe!)</l>
                  <l>She's fall'n I fear into that lazie, ſad,</l>
                  <l>And languiſhing diſeaſe call'd —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>The Green Sickneſſe.</l>
                  <l>'Tis true my dear <hi>Marcus,</hi> and as you were,</l>
                  <l>My phyſician in like caſe, ſo muſt ſome-body —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord <hi>Valerian!</hi> I have no skill in Augury,</l>
                  <l>But like the <hi>Omen,</hi> that when my wife ſaid</l>
                  <l>Some-body, mine-eye was inſtantly on you;</l>
                  <l>From thence, it glanced on my Lord <hi>Tiburtius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I lay my life, you come, to ſome ſuch end.</l>
                  <l>I read methinks, ſuch ſpeaking Characters,</l>
                  <l>In face and features, eye, and front, as plain,</l>
                  <l>And legible, as wrinkles in my <hi>Flavia's</hi> —</l>
                  <l>Forehead, was about to ſay, nay be not angry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, well, had I not been the honeſter</l>
                  <l>I know where, and what had been as legible.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, I fear'd thou would'ſt be angry, but no matter.</l>
                  <l>Ladies muſt nere be old: their husbands may.</l>
                  <l>Lords y'are wellcome; but chiefly my <hi>Valerian.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That (ſome-body) was ſuch a boding word.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord you honour me ſo much, that I</l>
                  <l>Seem courted by a happineſs, to which</l>
                  <l>My more ambitious thoughts, could hardly yet</l>
                  <l>Aſpire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>My <hi>Flavia,</hi> what ſayſt thou to the match?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>I like it not: I tell you husband, I</l>
                  <l>Diſlike it utterly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>That parents ſhould</l>
                  <l>Make matches for their children.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>I, now thou ſpeak'ſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>No, bring them face to face, and let them parley.</l>
                  <l>Ah! Tis the pretieſt thing to hear them chat</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:199600:10"/>
                  <l>So far from the matter: for love-ſick wantons,</l>
                  <l>Are as impertinent, as they, who lie,</l>
                  <l>Perplext in burning feavers — Love's a phrenſie,</l>
                  <l>As I remember forty years ago.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Twenty wife, th' art not ſo old.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                  <l>When one diſtracted was demanded whether</l>
                  <l>He were a married man: No, no, (ſaid he)</l>
                  <l>I am not yet ſo mad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! ha! my Lord:</l>
                  <l>My Wife has brought you now within the compaſſe</l>
                  <l>Of —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Madmen! 'Tis even ſo by <hi>Juno.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And after this a longing comes in breeders,</l>
                  <l>And what is this but a phantaſtick madneſſe?</l>
                  <l>Ha! ha! Waſt not a pretty longing think you:</l>
                  <l>(<hi>Fulvius Torquatus</hi> being Conſul) when</l>
                  <l>The Knights of <hi>Mauritania,</hi> brought to <hi>Rome</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A ſavage man, who <hi>Polyphemus</hi>-like,</l>
                  <l>Had but one eye: <hi>Torquatus</hi> Lady, then</l>
                  <l>Being with Child, and hearing of this Monſter,</l>
                  <l>Long'd; infinitely deſir'd to ſee him,</l>
                  <l>As he paſt by her door; but none it ſeems</l>
                  <l>Would bring him in: and out ſhe would not go</l>
                  <l>In th' abſence of her husband. What pity!</l>
                  <l>She loſt her longing, next her life. But then</l>
                  <l>You know my Lord what did enſue. The Senate</l>
                  <l>The Grave Senate decreed that Roman Ladies</l>
                  <l>Should not fail, but every one ſhould have</l>
                  <l>Her longing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Some come ſhort of that <hi>Flavia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>The more's the pity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Elſe they would not live</l>
                  <l>Sequeſtred as they do.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you ſo waggiſh ſtill?</l>
                  <l>But you (my Lord) you have a longing too. —
<stage>To Val.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not to ſee a one-eyed man, <hi>Monoculus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But a fair Lady, though I ſay't that ſhould not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>That indeed Madam, is my more humble ſuit.</l>
                  <l>And infinite deſire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>That <hi>Cis</hi> may have her longing, ha! ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Why <hi>Cecilie</hi> where are you? <hi>Palinodio?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No body there to wait? <hi>Anguſtula,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:199600:10"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Auguſtula.</stage>
                  <l>You too ſo narrow ear'd, you cannot hear?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam your pleaſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>That your Lady Miſtris</l>
                  <l>Come hither in a trice, inſtantly approach.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>Approach Madam, ſhe's in her Oratory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>I, ſhe flows in her Oratory; but</l>
                  <l>Let her leave that Eloquence, and tell me,</l>
                  <l>In plain terms expound what means</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Terence: Accede ad hanc ignem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>— <hi>ut Calefias magis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>That Madam,</l>
                  <l>I can <hi>enucleat:</hi> Come to this female fire</l>
                  <l>That thou mayſt be enflamed: Lord <hi>Tiburtius</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I was about to ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Cecily.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>But ſee (my Daughter,)</l>
                  <l>For that intent —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Muſt come to you, my Lord</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valerian.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I long to have that happineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Is ſhe not yet come? Oh! ſhe's here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <l>Come Madam ſince there is no remedy,</l>
                  <l>Set a good face on't; that I am ſure you have;</l>
                  <l>VVhy do you veyl it then? you are not <hi>Nupta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till then like other Ladies make the beſt</l>
                  <l>Of what you have: Beauty and Truth are two</l>
                  <l>That ſeek no Covert: Needs will come to light.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam what is your Ladyſhips pleaſure!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>A thing of nothing, only ſpell <hi>Roma</hi> backward.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis <hi>Amor</hi> Madam.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                  <l>True; 'tis Love my Girle.</l>
                  <l>Be as well vers'd 'ith Deed, as in the Word,</l>
                  <l>And by thy Love, this Lord ſhall be enrich'd.</l>
                  <l>But what is <hi>Amor</hi> paſſive?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <p>I am lov'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Here, by your ſervant, Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <l>I might have ſayd</l>
                  <l>As much: but younger brothers muſt be curb'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:199600:11"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>So, to her, to her, my Lord. She ſhall be yours</l>
                  <l>Come Sweet-heart, we'le ſit and ſee perſonated,</l>
                  <l>The lovely Courtſhips, of our younger years.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Ladies, your Parents have left you to your choice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <p>Then, I chooſe heaven.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Myne, is your ſelf on earth.</l>
                  <l>Or were I 'bove the ſpangled Arch with you,</l>
                  <l>I'de rival <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf in point of Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <l>In point of Love!</l>
                  <l>Beauty and goodneſs—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhich I admire in you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <l>Are the ſole Objects of a chaſter Love.</l>
                  <l>Goodneſs is courted by the Appetite,</l>
                  <l>As beauty ſhould be by the underſtanding:</l>
                  <l>On which two ſenſes properly attend,</l>
                  <l>To hear, and ſee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Witneſſe theſe happy ears,</l>
                  <l>Charm'd by your Muſick; and theſe happyer eyes,</l>
                  <l>Which gaze on th'object of their wiſhed bliſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <l>But fair and good affect a Monarchy,</l>
                  <l>Eſtabliſh'd by the will, ſole Sovereign,</l>
                  <l>To ſway within, the Microcoſme of Man,</l>
                  <l>To which the faculties, of ſoul, and body,</l>
                  <l>As motions, habits, actions, paſſions, are</l>
                  <l>Subordinate: yea, and concupiſcence</l>
                  <l>(Though a rebellious Vaſſal to the will,)</l>
                  <l>May be ſubjected.— Now if fair and good.</l>
                  <l>Be that you ſeek, it totally conſiſts,</l>
                  <l>In unity of eſſence; whence deriv'd</l>
                  <l>Are all the Fairs, and goodneſs you behold,</l>
                  <l>Which ſcatter'd here, and there, in ſeveral Creatures,</l>
                  <l>Are but dependants on the ſoveraign good.—</l>
                  <l>To reach to this; within the higheſt Region</l>
                  <l>Of the Soul, a love divine refiding,</l>
                  <l>Dos offer ſacrifice of awfull Prayer,</l>
                  <l>And Holocauſtes to the Divinity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>Tittle tattle! what's all this to th' purpoſe?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> is fair, and <hi>Jupiter</hi> is good.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, a proper man well qualified.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                  <l>I, Daughter, and all our hope of Offspring</l>
                  <l>Muſt be in thee and good <hi>Lucina</hi>'s aid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>And, my Lord <hi>Valerian</hi>'s help here! what <hi>a la mort.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:199600:11"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I am by th' ſtream diſmiſs'd to ſeek the ſource.</l>
                  <l>Caſt off to ſearch, a fairer then her ſelf.</l>
                  <l>Ah! if ſuch goodneſs, as reſides in her,</l>
                  <l>Dos but participate of that ſupreme,</l>
                  <l>And onely good, to that I muſt afpire</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tik.</speaker>
                  <l>had I but ſuch a ſpark from the immenſe</l>
                  <l>She ſpeaks of, my ambition ne're would ſeek,</l>
                  <l>A greater fire t'enflame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>No more would I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor you, nor you; what earthly ſouls you bear</l>
                  <l>Within your breſts! confin'd to carnal Iuſt:</l>
                  <l>Heaven is my choice, while here you court but duſt.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Hi'da! here's a wooing with a witneſs!</l>
                  <l>My Lord, the fooliſh Girle, is not yet capable,</l>
                  <l>Of th' happineſs which is atchiev'd by Love:</l>
                  <l>This was your fault that never would infuſe,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſweeter drops, diſtill'd from <hi>Venus</hi> roſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhy Sir, who would have thought one of her years,</l>
                  <l>Being now ſixteen and upward, could be ſo backward,</l>
                  <l>In learning that of Love, which in their Nonage</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Anguſta.</stage>
                  <l>Of teens others attain unto? why <hi>Anguſtula</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhere's your Lady?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Gone to her Cloſet, Madam.</l>
                  <l>So very ſad and penſive that it grieves me —</l>
                  <l>That ſhe may have her choice of two, and I of neither.
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord y'are welcom, this may now ſuffice</l>
                  <l>At the firſt puſh of Pike: let her retreat,</l>
                  <l>She ſhall come on again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>I, and at next encounter.</l>
                  <l>Daign ſmile for ſmile, and with a lovely glance</l>
                  <l>As boldly in the ſhock of Love advance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>So ſhall you ever oblige your ſervant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>And mee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Had I another Daughter, ſhe ſhould be yours.
<stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt</hi> Val. &amp; Tib.</stage>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                  <p>Unhappy wooer that has but verbal Cures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anguſtula!</hi> come thou diminitive wagg.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Call <hi>Palinodio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, he's here.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:199600:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>T'expect your Lordſhips pleaſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet heart! I have it; <hi>heareca,</hi> 'tis mine own.</l>
                  <l>The plot's layd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <l>If a Project 'twill never thrive</l>
                  <l>As we daily ſee in our projectors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>This Gentleman-Uſher ſhall act <hi>Valerian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And this witty well vers'd wanton, her mayd</l>
                  <l>Shall perſonate our daughter to make an</l>
                  <l>Introduction or Preamble to the grand Volume</l>
                  <l>Of Love, and teach he the rule of <hi>For the due joyning.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>VVho an't pleaſe you ſhall begin, for I am</l>
                  <l>Somewhat baſhfull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>The woman muſt alwayes</l>
                  <l>Have the laſt word: thou then ſhalt have the firſt.</l>
                  <l>But firſt call my daughter.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Cecilie.</stage>
                  <l>Come Daughter, ſit by me, and be attentive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Cecilie,</hi> from whence ſhould, I derive</l>
                  <l>Your Name <hi>Cecilie,</hi> but from that richer <hi>Sicilie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>An Iſland famous; <hi>Ceres</hi> darling, <hi>Italies</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Delight, Relief, and Granary: whoſe every</l>
                  <l>Luxurious Crop prevents from hungry Death,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand famiſhing for want of Grain.</l>
                  <l>Ah! then will you ſo fair and rich a Soyl,</l>
                  <l>So fertiliz'd with a more beauteous Crop,</l>
                  <l>Permit your ſervant, languiſh in your love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Hearken to this Daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah good my Lord ſhall I be th' Iſland <hi>Sicilie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Environ'd with the ſea, not married with</l>
                  <l>The neighbouring ſhoar? you teach me then a part</l>
                  <l>To live, a Virgin, which is my deſire.—</l>
                  <l>As my Lady I ſpake it.
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>But how will you, be fruitfull then, ſweet Lady?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſaid, now thou com'ſt to drive it home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>How like that fertile Iſle? or how ſhall I</l>
                  <l>But reap one crop of ſavours to enrich</l>
                  <l>Beyond deſert, your ſervant, who proteſtes —</l>
                  <l>He's at a non-plus— ah! fair would you daign</l>
                  <l>To ſowe within my heart one hopefull grain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>Of Muſtard-ſeed my Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199600:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Which mounting high,</l>
                  <l>We both reciprocal, ſhall multiply.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>I, keep her to that my Lord <hi>Valerian.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Now ile be more ſerious, for my Lady elſe will be angry.</l>
                  <l>A Virgins thoughts that ſpring from a chaſt ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Are ſuch a crop as fertile <hi>Sicily</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cannot produce: whoſe every lade's a ſword,</l>
                  <l>To ſliſe in two a thouſand amorous darts,</l>
                  <l>With which blind <hi>Cupid</hi> wounds but the impure.</l>
                  <l>Each knob, upon the ſtalk, a ſtop to vice,</l>
                  <l>Each ear of corn that riſeth from her heart,</l>
                  <l>More highly priz'd than all your belly grain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>I, now ſhe comes near the matter in hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Each petty husk, a cloſet in her breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Preſents a Viand on a Plate of gold,</l>
                  <l>To him whoſe love ſhe vows to live and dy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>But then where's the increaſe? to multiply</l>
                  <l>Fair Lady is what Nature has ordain'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>The Chryſtal cup's more pure that's never ſtain'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſhould we live, if ne're were till'd the Earth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>She was a Virgin firſt, and by chaſt birth,</l>
                  <l>Firſt fruits were grown e're ſown; ſuch ſhall be mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Tuſh theſe are words, Lady you muſt be mine.</l>
                  <l>I vow you muſt, elſe I ſhall pine and die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, ſo moſt Lovers fain, and ſwear, and lie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet, I am content to live and love withal;</l>
                  <l>You have an Organ and a Virginal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>On which I'le play for ſolace of my mind.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh that I (happy) might like favour find.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Now daughter, how like you this? ſhe frowns.</l>
                  <l>Come wife leave her to ruminate a while.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anguſta</hi> attend on me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Palinodio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <p>Here my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Come away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor Lord, nor now <hi>Valerian,</hi> I muſt ſay,
<stage>Exeunt. manet Cecilie.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Madam, I was not ſerious; did but play.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus am I taught to be a Pagan's love;</l>
                  <l>A Child to Parents who adore the Gods.</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Rome!</hi> thy Gods obſcene, would have me ſuch.</l>
                  <l>Not live as I have vow'd to him above,</l>
                  <l>Who has aſſign'd a Guardian to protect me.</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199600:13"/>
                  <l>Maugre the malice of th' infernal fiend,</l>
                  <l>And all his ſordid Vaſſals, ſtill ſhall ſpring,</l>
                  <l>My pure white Lilly, to my Sovereign King.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Act. II. Scene I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Palinodio <hi>with money and viands in a basket.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>NOw my good genius direct me, and my better Lady <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilie</hi> defend me, who ſends me this night, to ſeek in <hi>Via Appia,</hi> for a certain Cave or Grot, where lies hidden a holy man call'd <hi>Urban,</hi> and many Chriſtians with him, in this heavy perſecution, Now there are ſo many ſpies that lie in wait; that I have a fearful apprehenſion, I ſhall be apprehended; and carried before that cruel Judge <hi>Turcius Almachius.</hi> To prevent the worſt, I could find in my heart, to feed here of the beſt, and keep this purſe of money, for my private expences. O! but here's one within, call'd Conſcience, that tells me then, I am a wicked villain. Ha! let me ſee what hill have I before me. Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, 'tis the Temple dedicated <hi>Deo Ridiculo,</hi> to the God of Langhter. Ha, ha, ha, I cannot but laugh at the conceit. Even here lay <hi>Hannibal</hi> and beſieg'd the City, after he had ſlain forty thouſand brave Romans in the battel at <hi>Cannae.</hi> Here I ſay he lay till on the ſudden, there was ſuch laughing, and gigling round about his Army, that laugh'd-quite out of countenance, the couragious <hi>Hannibal,</hi> rais'd his ſiege, remov'd into <hi>Campania.</hi> Ha, ha, ha, this way is ſo full of briars and buſhes! ſome body may lie ſculking here. <stage n="†" place="margin">Enter <hi>Phantaſio,</hi> and lays hold on <hi>Palinodio's</hi> Cloak.</stage> Oh! I yield, I yield, I yield. The Officer has got my Cloak. Oh! how my heart goes a pit a pat, nine mile an honr: If he would now be ſcar'd away like <hi>Hannibal,</hi> I would make a ſhift to ſtrain a laugh. Ha, ha, ha, now I ſee the thief, a bramble buſh, laid hold of my Cloak. Ha, ha, ha, how I ſhould be laugh'd at now, if this were known? but now, now, now, I hear ſome body at my heels. Oh! ſure I look pale enough now to be taken for a Ghoſt. Ah! what am I now like, if not like a puny Serjeant, when he firſt handles his Mace, and cries I arreſt you, while he himſelf is fleeting and fluttering backward, moſt ſhamefully diſcovering the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in his retentive power. Or I am like a Cut-purſe (a young Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticioner) that ſeeing a purſe hanging by a womans ſide (as he fears <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199600:13"/>he may on the Gallowes:) thus with a trembling palſie ſtands in a quandary.
<stage>Stands trembling.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <p>Who goes there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>No body for I ſtand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <p>Who ſtands there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>No body, for I kneel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <p>Who kneels there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>No body, for I crawle.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <p>Then who crawles there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>No body, for I thus — <hi>Lies on his back with his heels upwards, ſtradling.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! now I ſee 'tis but ſome old forked ſtub of a tree, and here's the twiſt, which puts me in mind of that robuſtious <hi>Milo,</hi> who coming thus to the twin-like body of a tree, by main force rent them in two, when ſuddenly he falling in, they thus clap and clos'd together.
<stage>Pha. <hi>ſtretches out his legs, and claps them hard together</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>O! O!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <p>So <hi>Milo</hi> was ſlain,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>O my heels, my heels, O!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <l>Whom have we here <hi>Palinodio</hi> topſie turvy?</l>
                     <l>Not yet deliver'd the preſent to the reverent Biſhop</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Urban?</hi> My Lady fearing as much, ſent me after you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Would you had gone before, for me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <l>So I will: Come here's the Grotte.</l>
                     <l>Thrice with a gentle ſtamp but give the ſign,</l>
                     <l>And to this darkſome Cave ſhall way be made.
<stage>
                           <hi>They ſtamp. Urban</hi> aſcends.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Urb.</speaker>
                     <l>Who's there? if friends y'are welcome: ſo muſt be</l>
                     <l>Our enemies, who by heavens permiſſion,</l>
                     <l>Are but the Inſtruments to cut, and hew,</l>
                     <l>And ſquare us in this Quarry; we may lie</l>
                     <l>Fit for the Structure of Heavens Edifice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <l>May it pleaſe your reverence, my Lady <hi>Cecilie</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Preſents you w th theſe viands, and a purſe</l>
                     <l>Of an hundred Ducats for your ſelf and yours.</l>
                     <l>Hopes to be conſtant in her Faith and Vow,</l>
                     <l>If you to heaven for her vouchſafe to pray;</l>
                     <l>Which humbly ſhe deſires.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Urb.</speaker>
                     <l>We are oblig'd</l>
                     <l>To do no leſſe. Her charitable hand</l>
                     <l>May never ſee corruption: nor that pure</l>
                     <l>And ſanctified veſſel, where a treaſure,</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:199600:14"/>
                     <l>[Her ſoul] is habitant midſt chaſt deſires.</l>
                     <l>Farewel, heaven grant you may as ſafe return.
<stage>Deſcends.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>Come <hi>Palinodio</hi> now you'l lead the way.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I fear nothing, now I have a companion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Maximus <hi>and Officers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Look round, beſet the wayes, there, there they go.
<stage>Phantaſio ſlips away.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh let me come behind that I may not ſee him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Off.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I ſee but one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Lay hold, and apprehend him.
<stage>Palin. <hi>feigns himſelf ſick.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Off.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I have him, but cannot hold him up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Off.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Alas! he's in a ſwoon, fetch him again, he's gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Off.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>That I will, were he gone farther than he is.
<stage>Box in the ear.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay me! what are you my Maſters?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Off.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Villain what art thou? Art a Chriſtian?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>No Villain, Chriſtian I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Off.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>What art then?</l>
                     <l>What's thy Name?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Palinodio,</hi> to cant and recant,</l>
                     <l>Say and vnſay. I am (as many are now adayes)</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Nullifidian;</hi> have a conſcience of <hi>Chiverel,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And am content to ſay any thing for a quiet life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Betray thy fellow Chriſtians, or ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Or ſo, or ſo, ha, ha, ha, ha; yet I cannot but laugh</l>
                     <l>To think, how <hi>Hannibal,</hi> here in <hi>Via Appia,</hi> was laugh'd</l>
                     <l>Out of countenance. Ha, ha, ha, methinks I ſhould as well</l>
                     <l>Outlaugh theſe Officers, out of their little wits, for countenance</l>
                     <l>They have none to be laugh'd out of; ha, ha, ha.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Off.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>The fellow's mad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Palin.</speaker>
                     <p>Now I ſacrifice to the God of Laughter.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Almachius <hi>with Attendants.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Live we not ſtill in <hi>Rome?</hi> Or is not <hi>Rome</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The eye of Juſtice, ſplendor of the World?</l>
                     <l>Shall then blind Superſtition intrude?</l>
                     <l>t'obſcure the Iuſtre of our Deities?</l>
                     <l>Shall that baſe abject ſeum, and dregs of th' earth</l>
                     <l>Float on the ſurface of our Chryſtal ſtream?</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:199600:14"/>
                     <l>Chriſtians I mean, who firſt in <hi>Nero's</hi> time</l>
                     <l>Were by the flames which burnt our palaces</l>
                     <l>Diſcover'd, and convinc'd to be</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Flambeaux,</hi> and th' Incendiaries;</l>
                     <l>Becauſe they could not vindicate themſelves</l>
                     <l>Againſt our powerful Gods, for which their horrid</l>
                     <l>And enormous crime, their <hi>Coryphaeus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Was on a Gibbet topſie turvy hung,</l>
                     <l>While his companion (cauſe in a City born</l>
                     <l>That was enfranchiz'd) had Roman-like th'honour</l>
                     <l>To have his head ſtruck from his ſhoulders. Theſe,</l>
                     <l>Theſe were the traiterous pair who hither came</l>
                     <l>To ſow the Cockle of Sedition; which</l>
                     <l>As yet could nere be roote out; O <hi>Romans!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are you not <hi>Romans</hi> ſtill? have you not conquer'd</l>
                     <l>The vaſter Regions of th' Univerſe?</l>
                     <l>Yet ſuffer Piſmires, Pedants, Boyes and Girles,</l>
                     <l>t'apoſtatize, ſcorn, and defie our Gods?</l>
                     <l>Have you not Tortures? Manacles, and Racks?</l>
                     <l>Have you not Fire and Sword, and Ravenous Beaſts</l>
                     <l>To tear the Intrails of this curſed brood?</l>
                     <l>Slice off theſe <hi>Hydra</hi>'s ſtill increaſing heads,</l>
                     <l>And ſindge with flames of fire, like <hi>Hercules?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our Emperour commands, ſhew your <hi>Devoir.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our Gods command, ſhew then your <hi>Roman</hi> Zeal.</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Flamins,</hi> Sacred Prieſts, cry ſhame of you,</l>
                     <l>That ſuffer ſuch abortive Impes to ſcorn</l>
                     <l>Their Altars. <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf though patient long,</l>
                     <l>Begins to take his Thunderbolts in hand</l>
                     <l>To be reveng'd on you; which to prevent</l>
                     <l>Be vigilant: ſuppreſs this creeping <hi>Cancer.</hi> Be</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Romans,</hi> and you are what you ſhould be.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Maximus, Saphricius, <hi>and</hi> Palinodio.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Maximus?</hi> Welcome. Thy Name ſuperlative</l>
                     <l>Speaks what thou art. Say then, haſt thou diſrouted</l>
                     <l>Thoſe lurking Squadrons? forc'd them from their Cavernes,</l>
                     <l>Where in the night, conſcious of fouler crimes,</l>
                     <l>They with their ſuperſtitious rites, and fopperies</l>
                     <l>Exaſperate our Gods 'gainſt us, who ſuffer</l>
                     <l>Such ſacrilegious perſons; (rather vipers)</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:199600:15"/>
                     <l>T'eſcape unpuniſh'd: Vipers, which in their Birth,</l>
                     <l>(Pernicious) bring deſtruction to their Dams. —</l>
                     <l>So they to the Republick. Speak <hi>Maximus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And if thy ſervice ſhall deſerve reward,</l>
                     <l>The Gods, and we next to the Emperour,</l>
                     <l>Shall guerdon thine endeavours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord, I with my ſouldiers (ere the morn.</l>
                     <l>Had baniſht ſable night) as private as we could,</l>
                     <l>Went to ſurprize ſuch irreligious perſons</l>
                     <l>As are offenſive to the ſtate? yet 'twas</l>
                     <l>Our fortune but to light on two. A pair</l>
                     <l>Unparallell'd: one for a ſturdy Knave,</l>
                     <l>Th'other a fool, or if a rational man;</l>
                     <l>'Twas then a guilty Conſcience, with ſad fear,</l>
                     <l>Which did tranſport his brains beyond himſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Sirrah! why Sirrah! Speak'ſt not when I</l>
                     <l>But Sirrah thee? was not this blaſt enough</l>
                     <l>To make thee utter with a faltering tongue,</l>
                     <l>A more ſubmiſſive and obſequious plea,</l>
                     <l>To beg a pardon for thy foul delict.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>The toad is ſwelling, and begins to belch</l>
                     <l>The gall and venome of his poyſon'd breaſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah! I have a Rack.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>And I have limbs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>I have a Torture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>I patience to endure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>But I have ſcorching flames.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>Then let them burn.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt by morſels die: but piece by piece.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>All's one to me: at laſt I can but die.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, die a thouſand times and live again.</l>
                     <l>Or, if thou wilt, do but adore the Gods:</l>
                     <l>But ſacrifice to them, and thou art quit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Or die, or quit: A play at faſt and looſe,</l>
                     <l>I ſcorn to live by adoring of thy Gods,</l>
                     <l>Fear not to die, but dare in ſpight of them,</l>
                     <l>Yield this to fire or ſword, or beaſt, or flame,</l>
                     <l>To raiſe a Trophy to th' Immortal Power.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>I told you my Lord, he was a ſturdy Knave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>A <hi>Bragadochio</hi> this, a <hi>Famfarone.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Swells like a bubble, will the ſooner break.</l>
                     <l>Take him aſide. Nor Sirrah what are you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:199600:15"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Palin.</speaker>
                     <p>He's a wiſeman (my Lord) that knows what he is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah are you a ſervant of <hi>Jupiters?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jupiter</hi> would never entertain me</l>
                     <l>Into his ſervice, yet my ambition was</l>
                     <l>To have been a follower of his. Ha, ha, ha,</l>
                     <l>But his Queen <hi>Juno</hi> ſaid I had not wit</l>
                     <l>and craft enough to be a Courtier, ha, ha, ha.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Venus</hi> ſhe's a beautiful Lady:</l>
                     <l>I have plaid at ſpan-counter with her boy</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid.</hi> But he was blind, and ſo I burſt</l>
                     <l>His Bow and Arrows; ſince when I never was in love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah, will you ſacrifice to the Gods?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>And Goddeſſes too, tagg and ragg, to <hi>Smug,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vulcan</hi> the Blackſmith, and <hi>Priapus</hi> too,</l>
                     <l>With his fie for ſhame, to ſcare away the birds</l>
                     <l>That come to eat the Cherries and Mulberries, ha, ha, ha.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Maximus,</hi> what ſot have you brought me hither?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord he's ſervant to a Roman Lady.</l>
                     <l>And cauſe a fool he's fitter to be examin'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>In matter of nonſenſe. Let him be well whipt,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe diſcover what he is, and where</l>
                     <l>His Lady dwells.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, ha, ha, my Lady?</l>
                     <l>She's fairer than your Goddeſs <hi>Venus,</hi> ile ſtand to't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>At a Pillar thou ſhalt ſtand and be well whipt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Well then, every thing that's well, is not amiſs.</l>
                     <l>Farewel my Lord, I will not ſay I kiſs</l>
                     <l>Your Lordſhips hands: for then (if with the lip):</l>
                     <l>There were more rime, than reaſon in the whip.</l>
                     <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Sirrah I'le have you whipt</l>
                     <l>Out of this laughing humour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bacchus</hi> your God</l>
                     <l>To this invites. Let me drink wine, and quaffe pure,</l>
                     <l>And ſacrifice unto the God of Laugh—ture, ha, ha.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Away with them: Juſtice ſeems in diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>Until ſhe come to have her time and place.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199600:16"/>
                  <head>Scene <hi>3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Valerian <hi>and</hi> Anguſta.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord <hi>Valerian</hi> y' are welcome, as I may ſay.</l>
                     <l>And what I ſay I doubt not to make good. —</l>
                     <l>I have in your behalf ſolicited</l>
                     <l>So far my Lady; ſo urgently, that now</l>
                     <l>In our diſcourſe the onely ſubject, Love,</l>
                     <l>Is entertain'd: Books, Prayers, are laid aſide,</l>
                     <l>But now and then ſhe vents a ſigh (good Lady!)</l>
                     <l>So careful of my good. And why (ſays ſhe)</l>
                     <l>May'ſt thou not have like fortune? There's <hi>Tiburtiue</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My Lord <hi>Valerian</hi>'s brother, methinks he might</l>
                     <l>Affect thee; as deſerving as my ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Thy features are as good, thy favour ſuch,</l>
                     <l>As pleaſing every lineament: thy Beauty</l>
                     <l>Exceeding mine, at which (my Lord) I bluſht,</l>
                     <l>When parallelſ'd with ſuch a Paragon.</l>
                     <l>And with deep ſighs could hardly evaporate</l>
                     <l>That then intruſive love, which (I unworthy)</l>
                     <l>Fain would, but durſt not entertain. Yet then</l>
                     <l>As I reflected on our <hi>Latin frater,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(As much to ſay, as <hi>fere alter:</hi> almoſt</l>
                     <l>The ſame, or elſe another ſuch) I thought</l>
                     <l>If one to th' other be ſo near in blood,</l>
                     <l>And conſtitution, yea and ſimpathy,</l>
                     <l>Propenſe to love the ſame (as I am ſure)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tiburtius</hi> do's my Lady) ſince they cannot</l>
                     <l>Both ſhare in one; may not my Lord <hi>Tiburtius</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Reflect his eye on me, ſo near and dear</l>
                     <l>Unto her Ladiſhip? but then again</l>
                     <l>I check'd my too preſumptuous thoughts, and vow'd,</l>
                     <l>Howſoe're I were neglected in this kind,</l>
                     <l>My ſervice ſhould not be extenuated</l>
                     <l>In all good offices towards your Lordſhip</l>
                     <l>That may deſerve your favour, though not his love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou'ſt ſaid enough; and 'cauſe he riva's me,</l>
                     <l>Thus to divert the torrent of his love: —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>I think 'twere policy (my Lord) to turn</l>
                     <l>The Current this way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199600:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Right, I like it well.</l>
                     <l>Nor wants thy Love a baſe to build upon.</l>
                     <l>For 'tis not long fince thus I heard him ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>That in his eye thou wert not contemptible.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>No more but So:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>And though thou wert not a</l>
                     <l>Lady he could make thee one.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>That's ſomewhat indeed.</l>
                     <l>But what more my good Lord I beſeech you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay there he fixt a period to his ſpeech.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>And ended with Lady. Noble <hi>Tiburtius?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Made a full point at Lady; as if he had</l>
                     <l>Then pointed at <hi>Anguſta</hi> to make <hi>Auguſta.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Why ſhould not we fair ones ſtand on our points?</l>
                     <l>That Beauty may be Zenith point above:</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Nadir</hi> (portion) to be trampled on)</l>
                     <l>The point beneath. But you my Lord have all;</l>
                     <l>Beauty and wealth, and vertue to be priz'd,</l>
                     <l>In her who now cannot be ſeen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſeen?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>No more than <hi>Cynthia</hi> with her ſilver Creſt</l>
                     <l>Which (modeſt) ſometimes veyls her beauteous face.</l>
                     <l>Yet were my Lord <hi>Tiburtius</hi> here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Tiburtius.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>See, here he comes,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>But not with ſuch a ſparkling eye</l>
                     <l>Nor half ſo quick as yours my Lord, ay me!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>Now Fair <hi>Anguſta</hi> ſigh and I ſo nigh?</l>
                     <l>Thou may'ſt be Lady yet before thou dy'ſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady! as he ended ſo he begins.</l>
                     <l>Indeed my Lord, 'tis more to make one ſuch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>As thou art?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>No my Lord, rather as I</l>
                     <l>Would be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>She's in good earneſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Earneſt my Lord?</l>
                     <l>Yes, and you may give me earneſt, that your love</l>
                     <l>Shall make me ſuch. You'l love my Lady too;</l>
                     <l>You will? O the ambition of a younger</l>
                     <l>Brother! And you my Lord, you can diſſemble,</l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:199600:17"/>
                     <l>Tell me your brother ſaid that he could make</l>
                     <l>Me a Lady?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>But that he would, I did not ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>There's yours, you may be gone, here lies my way.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>So here's a flirt: ſuch as are now adayes,</l>
                     <l>That muſt be fed with Gold: and not content</l>
                     <l>With that, muſt have a husband too, with a</l>
                     <l>Miſchief. Ah! that a Lady's love ſhould be</l>
                     <l>Thus pandar'd by a Gypſie, 'tis too true</l>
                     <l>What her fair Lady ſpake 'twixt wo and woe</l>
                     <l>There's but ſmall difference.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord let's go.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>And leave this trifling fuit, 'turns woo, to wo.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Anguſta <hi>and calls</hi> Tiburtius <hi>behinde as he goes out.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, a word.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay'ſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Could you think me</l>
                     <l>So immodeſt as to Court you thus?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>No I 'twas your brothers plot, his policy,</l>
                     <l>That like a Loadſtone by attractive power,</l>
                     <l>I might draw back your love from my good Lady,</l>
                     <l>(Who's in affection yours) that only he</l>
                     <l>Might have free paſſage to enjoy her love.</l>
                     <l>Should I be thus magnetique, I were baſe.</l>
                     <l>I am wholly yours: My ſervice wholly bent,</l>
                     <l>That you may gain this pretious Gemme, not he,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Art ſerious?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Elſe were moſt unworthy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>Take this.
<stage>Gives her Money.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>A Trifle for the preſent, ſhalt have more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Brother may ſuſpect.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I'le away.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Adieu moſt worthy Lord. Ha! ha! thus Love</l>
                     <l>Is often now adayes dear bought and ſold.—</l>
                     <l>If not himſelf, at leaſt I have his gold.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:199600:17"/>
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Nicephorus Solus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>MY troubled thoughts perplex, while Conſcience here</l>
                     <l>Upbraids me with diſſimulation,</l>
                     <l>To my dear friend <hi>Saphricius;</hi> whom I long,</l>
                     <l>With pity have obſerv'd, to entertain</l>
                     <l>Too much of complacence; or which is worſe,</l>
                     <l>Vain glory to adde a luſtre to his actions,</l>
                     <l>Which dos diminiſh, not augment their worth.</l>
                     <l>For though Heaven daigns to promiſe due reward,</l>
                     <l>Yet he, reſerves the honour to himſelf;</l>
                     <l>Which, while my friend uſurps, and I connive,</l>
                     <l>Yea, not ſo much, as intimate a crime,</l>
                     <l>I am no faithfull friend; which I have ſworn</l>
                     <l>To be till death.— ah! diſſimulation!</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhouldſt not be a Vice, ſince nor a King,</l>
                     <l>Can reign without thee, nor a boſom friend,</l>
                     <l>Preſerve intire that ſacred Amity,</l>
                     <l>Which I unhappily (I fear) may violate—</l>
                     <l>No, my <hi>Saphricius,</hi> is ſo nobly good,</l>
                     <l>He'le rather render thanks, than deem me harſh,</l>
                     <l>Chide, cauſe I've been too backward in advice.—</l>
                     <l>A friend in Counſel, muſt not be too nice.</l>
                     <l>See here he comes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>My dear <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> y'are happily encounter'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>My beſt and only friend <hi>Saphricius!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Methinks our daily interviews and kinde</l>
                     <l>Embraces do enſoul each others breſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Abſent from you</l>
                     <l>Methought my heart had but the moity</l>
                     <l>Of life: was but a Cipher, till the digit</l>
                     <l>(Your heart conjoyn'd) ſummes up my happineſſe.—</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Stoick</hi> was miſtaken who avouch'd</l>
                     <l>A hearty, true, faithfull, and loyal friend</l>
                     <l>Long ſought, is ſeldom found, and hardly kept;</l>
                     <l>Whereas our friendſhip has from younger years,</l>
                     <l>Been ever pregnant, like a forward Spring,</l>
                     <l>As laſting as the Plant <hi>Live-ever:</hi> My Deareſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Niſus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:199600:18"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <p>My <hi>Euryalus!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>My faithfull <hi>Achates.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <p>My ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Selfly the ſame, I live in thee,</l>
                     <l>But ſhould we die (for now <hi>Almachius</hi> vows</l>
                     <l>The death of Chriſtians) may our twin-like ſouls</l>
                     <l>Be joyntly breath'd to mount to equal bliſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>A happy period to our friendſhip, when</l>
                     <l>Chang'd, 'tis ſtill a more tranſcendent Love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>True, but tell me my <hi>Nicephorus.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did I not yeſterday confute the Pagan</l>
                     <l>With whom I diſputed; kill'd him dead with</l>
                     <l>A Syllogyſme: Lodg'd him in <hi>Bocardo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And then you heard, how the miſcreant (enrag'd)</l>
                     <l>Threaten'd to complain to <hi>Almachius:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Menac'd tortures, and death. At this (tell me)</l>
                     <l>Did I ſo much as ſympathize with terrour?</l>
                     <l>Nay did you not obſerve a chearfull look,</l>
                     <l>Like that of morn that uſhers a ſair day?</l>
                     <l>Was it not ſo <hi>Nicephorus?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>Moſt true it was,</l>
                     <l>But.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>But? why Sir bring you the But</l>
                     <l>And then I'le fix the white i'th midſt; as much of</l>
                     <l>Candour as a friend can bring. But? and then ſilent?</l>
                     <l>On! your too cautious (friend) pray uſe a freedom</l>
                     <l>And that impartially.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, I but gently whiſper</l>
                     <l>(My dear <hi>Saphricius</hi>) what I have obſerv'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>As freely vent it forth, as ſharply too,</l>
                     <l>As when rough <hi>Boreas</hi> bluſters in the Ayre.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>Why then — but you'l be angry, will you not?</l>
                     <l>Should I but tell you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>What is't I dare not hear?</l>
                     <l>What Obloquy can blaſt mine innocence?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, 'tis but a <hi>Peccadillo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Not ſo much as a defect, or omiſſion; rather</l>
                     <l>A ſupererrogation which I many times have noted</l>
                     <l>VVhen the fact ſpake of it ſelf, to blazon it the more</l>
                     <l>(Like to a curious Limner) you heighten'd it;</l>
                     <l>Extoll'd and magnifi'd the work, yet in</l>
                     <l>An humble ſeeming way; which ſome too raſh</l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:199600:18"/>
                     <l>VVould judge to be vain-glory.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>So, ſo, you mince it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay good <hi>Saphricius</hi> wrinckle not your brow;</l>
                     <l>I may miſtake.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Then I will tell you Sir;</l>
                     <l>'Twas a reflexive luſtre from my actions</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe brighter coruſcation was too fierce</l>
                     <l>For ſuch weak eyes to gaze on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray be not angry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>No, muſt let your pride</l>
                     <l>And ſawcy Arrogance curb what is generous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay dear <hi>Saphricius,</hi> be not ſo incens'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>Hence Sycophant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <p>Steep not your tongue in gall.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>Drench it abſynth, I—ſpurn at my Actions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>But like the loving Mare which oft we ſee</l>
                     <l>Spares not to kick her young and tender foal,</l>
                     <l>Yet hurts it not. I was as wary not to give offence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Away, thy friendſhip is a meer Impoſture,</l>
                     <l>Now Experience tells a friend is hardly found.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>More hardly kept, ſince you are fleeting thus</l>
                     <l>But for a word.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>A word? a tempeſt rather, ſuch a blaſt</l>
                     <l>As has for ever ſhatter'd that goodly Veſſel</l>
                     <l>Your friend-ſhip, Sir; a Ship wherein I ſayl'd</l>
                     <l>Secure theſe twenty years: but now I finde</l>
                     <l>The Pilot treachetous, and his Sea-ſtarre</l>
                     <l>But proper intereſt: then let it ſplit;</l>
                     <l>For ever ſuffer wreck: And this bent brow</l>
                     <l>Contract eternal ſrowns.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah! was it not</l>
                     <l>A fault in me, that did not heretofore</l>
                     <l>In th'Infancy of friendſhip make that known</l>
                     <l>VVhich now habitual is a ſecond Nature.</l>
                     <l>But then I fear'd to loſe him in the Nonage</l>
                     <l>Of Amity: more ſolid now I thought</l>
                     <l>It could not but ſubſiſt immoveable</l>
                     <l>Yet, I hope I ſhall recover him, if not,</l>
                     <l>With that ſtern <hi>Stoick</hi> I will not contend</l>
                     <l>That ſaid, 'tis hard to find and keep a Friend.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:199600:19"/>
                  <head>ACT III. Scene I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Phantaſio <hi>and</hi> Metricio, <hi>with Songs.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>M <hi>Etricio,</hi> Come to the Barre.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>Call at the Barre</l>
                     <l>Thou wouldſt ſay for a quart of richer Wine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <l>No, come to the Barre, I ſay, I muſt arraign thee</l>
                     <l>For Theft and Burglary. Theft in a high degree,</l>
                     <l>Cauſe in thy Poems thou haſt enrich'd thy Verſe</l>
                     <l>With others labours. Burglary, becauſe</l>
                     <l>Th' haſt violently broken, into the Magazines</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Apollo,</hi> ranſack't, and rob'd, and tane away,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Invito Domino, hos ego verſiculos.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>Why good my Lord <hi>Phantaſio,</hi> ſay 'twere ſo,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nil dictum quod non dictum prius.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay there</l>
                     <l>Y' are in an errour too: th' Orator ſays</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dixi,</hi> the Poet <hi>Cecini,</hi> th' one ſays</l>
                     <l>At th'end of his Oration, <hi>I have ſaid;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Th' other <hi>I have ſung,</hi> at th' end of his Poem;</l>
                     <l>I will not therefore ask what thou canſt ſay</l>
                     <l>For thy ſelf (Poet) but, what canſt thou ſing?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <p>Then what I ſpeak (my Lord) muſt be in rhime.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſpeak, but ſing, I ſay, and i'le keep time.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Song.</head>
                        <l>Met. <hi>Then fraught with</hi> Crotchets <hi>and with</hi> Quavers,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'Tis for you we are ſuch ſhavers.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If by theft we break the Law,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'Tis for your</hi> Sol, Fa, Mi, La;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That you may have, for your Notes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Songs, to fill your warbling Throats.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What were elſe all that you ſing,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But a</hi> Sol, Fa, <hi>ſenſe-leſs thing?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What</hi> Chromatiques, <hi>what were</hi> Brawles?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What your</hi> Ditones, Intervals?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And if all your Songs were gone,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What were</hi> Diateſſaron?</l>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:199600:19"/>
                        <l>Diatonicks <hi>would not pleaſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What were all your</hi> Syncopes?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What your</hi> Meſons, Hypatons?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Or your</hi> Hyperboleons?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What your</hi> Nothi <hi>(baſtards) ha!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>You beget in</hi> Fa, Sol, Fa?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Moods not apt for</hi> Diapente,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet</hi> Fa mi <hi>ſometimes has twenty.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <l>Here Poet, here's for thy pains.— Nothing. ha! ha!</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ut re mi nil donas</hi> but <hi>Fa,</hi> there is wit,</l>
                     <l>And I am thy <hi>Sole</hi> Friend, <hi>La</hi> then we be quit.</l>
                     <l>But come hither in good earneſt, <hi>Metricio.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The laſt Sonnet here, which I have ſet to'th Organ</l>
                     <l>Pleaſes me well, but will not ſo my Lord <hi>Marcus.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis too ſerious.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>Such only my Lady deſires</l>
                     <l>Otherwiſe thou know'ſt my humour is</l>
                     <l>For light Ayres, and pleaſant <hi>Madrigales.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But ſhe'l have none but grave and ſubſtantiall.—</l>
                     <l>A Poet according to the Greek <hi>Etymon</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is a Maker, and ſo as in the Court,</l>
                     <l>There be ſome Creatures made, ſolid, and ſerviceable;</l>
                     <l>Others legier and ayrie; ſo are made by us</l>
                     <l>Poems, and Sonnets.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <l>But here too, you entrench</l>
                     <l>Upon the Muſitian.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>I, when 'tis for my purpoſe</l>
                     <l>A Poet has his Long and his Large ſometimes,</l>
                     <l>With a prolix and tedious Preamble.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sic coſtam longo ſubduximus Apenino.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Another has his <hi>Brief</hi> in a <hi>Spnnet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And a <hi>Seml-brief</hi> in an Epigram</l>
                     <l>VVhen it ends acutely. But will my Lady</l>
                     <l>Sing that my Sonnet next?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <l>She will: but his Lordſhip</l>
                     <l>Muſt not hear, nor ſee it: he's all for light Ayres,</l>
                     <l>Amorous Dities that his Daughter may</l>
                     <l>Reſolve to marry the young Lord <hi>Valeran.</hi>
                        <stage>Phan. <hi>ſnatches the Verſes, and attempts to read.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me ſee, <hi>Mount, mount, my ſoul.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay <hi>Phantaſio</hi> let me read and grace</l>
                     <l>My own, you in <hi>Prick-ſing,</hi> I better vers'd</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:199600:20"/>
                     <l>In <hi>Coma's, Colons, Semi-briefs, Periods, Et caetera.</hi>
                        <stage>Reads.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mount, mount my ſoul, mount with a higher ſtrain</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From this ſad vale, where pleaſure mixt with pain,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Can have no</hi> Alt. <hi>Heaven is my dwelling place,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And earth below, for mourning, is the baſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I live to love, but not to match with grief,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Long, a Large, I rather chooſe a brief,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vain Love! ſhort life! ah Heaven new ſet my Song,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Change but one Note, a</hi> Brief <hi>into a</hi> Long.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <p>But if my Lord hear this!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>Let him, and ſwear,</l>
                     <l>By all the gods, his daughter is my Miſtris;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <p>See here comes my Lord <hi>Valerian,</hi> let's withdraw.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anguſta</hi> whiſpering, ſhe's a very Sharke.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Valerian <hi>and</hi> Anguſta.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay my Lord, could you think I could be ſo</l>
                     <l>Uncivil, but that I would as well tax you,</l>
                     <l>As him, that no exceptions might be taken.</l>
                     <l>You little know his drift. He under-hand</l>
                     <l>Offers me thouſands to endear his Love,</l>
                     <l>Unto my Lady, which I'le never do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>VVell ſaid, the ſum I promis'd, ſhall be thine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Thus then my Lord, as I unveyl a heart</l>
                     <l>Unfaign'd unto your Lordſhip: I diſplay</l>
                     <l>This Curtain, where a Voyce ſhall firſt invite.</l>
                     <l>Your Ear to liſten, next to pleaſe your ſight.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Cecilie <hi>ſings within,</hi> Mount, mount, &amp;c. <hi>and after ſht has ſang it, ſhe enters,</hi> Anguſta <hi>following.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, y'are welcome.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>So breaths a ſweet perfume,</l>
                     <l>When milder <hi>Zephyres</hi> ventilate the Creſtes</l>
                     <l>Of ſweet <hi>Arabian</hi> Spiceries. VVelcome?</l>
                     <l>This only word, has here infus'd more heat</l>
                     <l>Than can bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> to the chilling earth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Miſtake me not (my Lord) VVelcom's a word</l>
                     <l>Of civil Courteſie. I a <hi>Roman</hi> bred,</l>
                     <l>And nobly born, ſhould rudely ſeem to treat</l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:199600:20"/>
                     <l>One of your Rank, ſhould I omit this one,</l>
                     <l>So courſe a Complement.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet, 'tis to me,</l>
                     <l>If reall, (as I am ſure it is) a word,</l>
                     <l>That bodes a happineſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true, my Lord,</l>
                     <l>A happineſs tranſcendent, to enrich</l>
                     <l>A ſoul, with more, than all the beauties, honours,</l>
                     <l>Pleaſures, or wealth, can now, or could conferre.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, with your favour, this far fetch'd ſtrain,</l>
                     <l>Mounts 'bove the pitch of Love, which is the Aym,</l>
                     <l>And ſcope of my Ambition.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah, Sir, how then</l>
                     <l>Shall we mix ſoul with ſoul, as well as loves?</l>
                     <l>If mine above the daring Eagle ſoare,</l>
                     <l>And cleave Heavens glorious Arch, ſhall your dull ſoul</l>
                     <l>Lie wrap'd in Earth below? give me a ſoul</l>
                     <l>Can tower at leaſt above the waking Lark,</l>
                     <l>And contemplate 'bove the eternal joyes;</l>
                     <l>Elſe what is it for me, and my <hi>Valerian,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To lye encircl'd in each others Arms?</l>
                     <l>If ever I ſhall come to give my hand,</l>
                     <l>And plight my troth; ſhall not a mutual hand,</l>
                     <l>That may cooperate with mine, be joyn'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt willingly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>And ſhall not then your heart</l>
                     <l>Conſpire with mine, with an unanimous</l>
                     <l>Conſent?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt freely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>If then but to one Eſſence,</l>
                     <l>And Power immortal I lift heart and hands,</l>
                     <l>VVill you not joyn with me and do the like?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>I will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>You'l be a Chriſtian, then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>O! ſtay.</l>
                     <l>You urge too far, what by Philoſophy</l>
                     <l>I have learn'd, you may perſwade me to; but more,</l>
                     <l>VVhy ſhould you crave? we both will worſhip one,</l>
                     <l>Acknowledge one, but ſacrifice to one.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed I was too forward, and hereby</l>
                     <l>May chance to be, like other Virgins, forc'd</l>
                     <l>To be your Love; by menacing of Death.</l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:199600:21"/>
                     <l>Or by my father (ſhould you make this known)</l>
                     <l>May be conſtrain'd to entertain your love,</l>
                     <l>Which wreſted, cannot be, what you deſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>No Lady, fear not me; e're I betray</l>
                     <l>A beauty ſo endow'd with vertues,</l>
                     <l>Heaven ſtrike me with a Thunder-bolt, or,</l>
                     <l>May love become abortive, and what here,</l>
                     <l>I have t'expreſs the notions of my ſoul,</l>
                     <l>May it be rent from my more treacherous Jaws.</l>
                     <l>See in a happy hour my Lord and Lady,</l>
                     <l>Your Parents come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Marcus <hi>and</hi> Flavia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>So, hand in hand; ſo may your hearts be linkt</l>
                     <l>And after more, but why doſt frown my girl?</l>
                     <l>Love has a noſegay all compos'd of ſweets.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Amor, et melle et felle eſt jucundiſſimus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Come honey, come gall, Love muſt abound in joy.</l>
                     <l>So thou (my Girle.)</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, you are the tree,</l>
                     <l>I, but the tender bud, yet while you flouriſh</l>
                     <l>I cannot droop or wither.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flav.</speaker>
                     <l>Bad me no buds.</l>
                     <l>Thou art a tree thy ſelf, apt to bring fruit,</l>
                     <l>But with my Lord <hi>Valerian</hi>'s help here, daughter,</l>
                     <l>You know my meaning.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>I, ſhe muſt be eſpous'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>How my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>Promis'd, betroth'd, and what not,</l>
                     <l>That may unite a pair, and make but one?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <p>I, daughter, it muſt be ſo, how ſay you my Lord?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>With her conſent you tender that to me,</l>
                     <l>Which nor the Gods can better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>How my Lord?</l>
                     <l>The Gods?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis but a word of courſe ſweet Lady:</l>
                     <l>One day, nor makes, nor can deſtroy a habit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord th'affair in hand do's ſo import</l>
                     <l>That of it ſelf, beſides my humble prayer,</l>
                     <l>It craves a time to pauſe, and weigh each —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:199600:21"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>Each pudding? tell us of pauſing and weighing now?</l>
                     <l>Tell us of time? he wears his Locks before.</l>
                     <l>How many beauteous Ladies have I known,</l>
                     <l>Who in their prime of youth, could not (forſooth)</l>
                     <l>Nor love this Noble Knight, nor that brave Lord;</l>
                     <l>Would have they know not what: lik'd not their Garb,</l>
                     <l>Or were not ſo gentile: or elſe their ſhape</l>
                     <l>And perſonage was not ſo compleat and abſolute.</l>
                     <l>In their eye as they deſir'd: Thus trifling</l>
                     <l>With time, they loſt their better fortunes,</l>
                     <l>Till Age grew on, and beauty was thereby</l>
                     <l>Diſparag'd: Then a husband, nor ſo rich,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſo proper; any then was welcome!</l>
                     <l>Yet to conſider, you would have more time</l>
                     <l>Daughter? <hi>O tempora! O mores!</hi> Time?</l>
                     <l>Why he has wings.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo has Love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>But time</l>
                     <l>Outſtrips him: therefore now my Girle, reſolve.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>She's baſhful, here, here, my Lord, ſhe's yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>I, ſilence is conſent, take he my Lord.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hymen, Hymen, O Hymenaee, Hymen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>So, we'le leave you for a while; ſhe alone</l>
                     <l>My Lord with you, in a familiar way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>Will be: (doubt it not) ſhe'le be tractable.</l>
                     <l>Daughter, <hi>Venus</hi> be with thee, and <hi>Adoms</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be thy Companion. Come my Lord let's away:</l>
                     <l>To prepare for the Nuptials.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Now's our joy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah, ha, oh!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>O do not blaſt ſweet Lady,</l>
                     <l>Blaſt not the tender bud of blooming Love</l>
                     <l>With ſuch ſad ſighs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Daphne</hi> your fables tell,</l>
                     <l>Purſu'd by your <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Not mine Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Was metamorphos'd, and a Lawrel grew:</l>
                     <l>So ſhe eſcap'd — I muſt retire awhile. <hi>weeps.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:199600:22"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Metricio <hi>and</hi> Phantaſio, <hi>and</hi> Anguſta.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>But do not weep.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>No Madam, for my Lord</l>
                     <l>Your father has commanded me to make</l>
                     <l>An <hi>Epithalamium,</hi> to celebrate</l>
                     <l>This Feſtival, and ſolemn day deſign'd</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Hymen's</hi> Revels.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>And I muſt be</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Paranymph.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>And I the <hi>Pronuba,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For you Madam the <hi>Nymph</hi> and <hi>Nupta</hi> too</l>
                     <l>Ere it be long.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>For me a watry Nymph,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe eyes are ſteep'd in tears, and throbbing heart</l>
                     <l>Involv'd with grief— Ah! Heaven new ſet my Song,</l>
                     <l>Change but one note, a <hi>Brief</hi> into a <hi>Long.</hi>
                        <stage>Swounes.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lady ſwounes away: Help, help my Lord.</l>
                     <l>Madam! what die before the Wedding Day?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Day? Day? I ſaw indeed a glimpſe of Day,</l>
                     <l>And thither I was haſt'ning: Why didſt call</l>
                     <l>Me back, t'inveſt with diſmal Night? the Day</l>
                     <l>Was dawning, as I clos'd my heavy eyes,</l>
                     <l>To be made happy by eternal light.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis but a paſſion of the heart my Lord,</l>
                     <l>And now the worſt is paſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>I am glad to hear it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>O! were <hi>Tiburtius</hi> mine, would I do thus?</l>
                     <l>Would I ſo near the Wedding Day retract,</l>
                     <l>What I had done? My Lord you heard her ſay</l>
                     <l>Retirement now was her deſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>You'l have</l>
                     <l>A ſpecial care?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Of her, and you my Lord,</l>
                     <l>For now, your lives are one, as are your Loves,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>And let me hear</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Each hour and moment too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah ſtill go linkt together, wo and woo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199600:22"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Officers and</hi> Palinodio <hi>in the midſt, with his hands ty'd, and led by a rope.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Come along there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>I, here's the ſhort and long</l>
                     <l>Of the buſineſs: either to betray my Lady Biſhop <hi>Urban</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By a long miſchief, or endure a ſhort, but a ſharp whipping.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="2">2. Sirrah I'le prick you forward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay forget not</l>
                     <l>(I prethee) thy Office, good Carman: whip not the Cart, but</l>
                     <l>The Jade that draws me there: Or let the Cart go before</l>
                     <l>The horſe † ſo now whip and ſpare not.
<stage>Skips before his Leader.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="2">2. Back Sirrah, and keep your way.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>If this be the way to happineſs, let them walk in it</l>
                     <l>That will, not I.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Not you Sirrah? why what are you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>A Gentleman Uſher I am,</l>
                     <l>But now am uſher'd by a Rogue, and back'd by a Raſcal.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <l>2. Sirrah your hide ſhall pay for this, printed with Rubrick</l>
                     <l>Letters, like your red rag there, that ſo ſawcy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah! good people was ever Gentleman-Uſher thus abus'd?</l>
                     <l>If gaming or wenching had forc'd one of my Calling to</l>
                     <l>Lay his Pluſh Suit to pawn, and wait on his Lady in</l>
                     <l>A thread-bare Cloak and Clothes? I never did ſo, though</l>
                     <l>Another of our Profeſſion ſtole his Ladies Jewels, and</l>
                     <l>Pawn'd them to the Broker; I never did ſo: yet you ſee</l>
                     <l>Innocence may ſuffer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Thou an Innocent, a Fool and a Knave thou art.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee untie me then, and let us ſhake hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Sirrah the Poſt is near; then—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay then he may bring newes for my releaſe,</l>
                     <l>At leaſt ſome of my Ladies houſe may look</l>
                     <l>Out there. O here comes Madam <hi>Anguſta.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Anguſta.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Why how now <hi>Palinodio,</hi> dragg'd home like a runnaway Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentce, I thought you had lov'd my Lady better than ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſhe jeers me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay let me untie thy hands, that it may be ſaid thou com'ſt home willingly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:199600:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>As willingly as ever came Wench to her Comrade, when ſhe wanted money.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Why how now bold <hi>Beatrice!</hi> can you juſtifie this Act?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Tiburtius.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>At leaſt, here comes one that will. My Lord you love my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy well, and therefore would not ſee her Dog wrong'd; much leſs her Servant here, and Gentleman Uſher.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>You Varlets, let him go.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="2">2. Why Sir he's a Chriſtian.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>But a Roman withal I am. 'Twould ne're have griev'd me to have been whipt as a Chriſtian; but as a Roman could ne're have been able to have waſh'd away the diſgrace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah put on his Doublet, button it you Sirrah, and that ſpeedily.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſo now I have my Gentleman and Taylor to wait on me, thus for a good Cauſe, honour attends upon diſgrace:</l>
                     <l>And I who whilome was contemn'd as no-man,</l>
                     <l>Am treated now, and honour'd like a Roman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="2">2. You'l anſwer this? my Lord <hi>Almachius</hi> ſhall know it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Hence Raſcalls, or —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Hence you baſe Canniballs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="2">2. Sirrah we ſhall meet with you again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>No, if I can help it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Yes Sirrah this ſhall reach you, go to.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Firſt may a halter ſtretch you, go two;</l>
                     <l>One halter will ſerve to hang you both.
<stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt Officers and</hi> Palin. <hi>at ſeveral Doors.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Lady, how goes the ſquares here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>So, with Lady</l>
                     <l>He begins again, as he clos'd the period:</l>
                     <l>Squares my Lord? Fortune's wheel turns round.</l>
                     <l>Your Brother, and my Lady were eſpous'd.</l>
                     <l>Ah my Lord that you had been ſo near the Mark!</l>
                     <l>Married in a manner they were.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>And are they not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay this night was deſign'd for bedding.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>And is't not ſtill?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſay my Lord it is.</l>
                     <l>If you'l give what you promis'd —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>And add more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le paſſe my word (and faithful) as I am)</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:199600:23"/>
                     <l>You ſhall anticipate by free acceſs</l>
                     <l>Unto her Chamber. And to augment your hopes,</l>
                     <l>What I avouch is truth. No ſooner were</l>
                     <l>Th' Eſpouſals finiſh'd, but ſhe, drencht in tears,</l>
                     <l>Fell in a ſwoun to th' earth: and what ſhe then</l>
                     <l>Was muttering, I beſt know, who rais'd her up.—</l>
                     <l>That what her parents by conſtraint had done,</l>
                     <l>Was no act of hers: And other words beſides.</l>
                     <l>Which —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>When thou art, as thou deſerv'ſt to be Enrich'd by this, and more which I will give,
<stage>Gives her a Purſe of money.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou wilt diſcover.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>And to make all ſure,</l>
                     <l>'Twixt eight and nine, come to the Poſtern Gate,</l>
                     <l>I'le let you in, and bring you to her Chamber door.</l>
                     <l>But I muſt not be ſeen: yet if you ſee</l>
                     <l>Some counter-mand which comes from her, as yet</l>
                     <l>To me unknown (but ſuch a thing may be)</l>
                     <l>Then — Noble Sir, lay not the fault on me:</l>
                     <l>But that which ſways in Marriage; Deſtiny.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>But if my Brother come and find me there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>As though I could not that prevent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>But how?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>One word can do't, have we not every day</l>
                     <l>A world of tatling Viſitants that come</l>
                     <l>To ſee, or to be ſeen, or idlely chat?</l>
                     <l>To theſe I ſay my Lady is not well.</l>
                     <l>There's no reply 'gainſt this. Nor will your brother</l>
                     <l>Make doubt of this, who lately left her in</l>
                     <l>Her fainting fits.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou will't not fail?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Farewel, till then.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Fortune attend your Lordſhip.</l>
                     <l>He's gone—Hum! — now am I at my wits end,</l>
                     <l>Like one who his promis'd two Creditors</l>
                     <l>To pay the ſame ſum of money, when he has,</l>
                     <l>But that in all the world. What ſhall I do?</l>
                     <l>Or which way turn to diſ-engage my ſelf?</l>
                     <l>Tuſh! An excuſe a woman (ſudden) brings</l>
                     <l>(When tax'd) by touching of her apron ſtrings.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:199600:24"/>
                  <head>ACT. IV. Scene 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Flouriſh. Enter</hi> Marcus, Flavia, Metricio, Phantaſio, Palinodio, Anguſta, Cecilie.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>THe <hi>Negra</hi> Night, though ſhe has vail'd the skies,</l>
                     <l>And baniſh'd hence the luſtre of the day,</l>
                     <l>Seems with the Muſick to applaud this hour:</l>
                     <l>And with her flaming tapers ſhews the way</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſweet Girle.</l>
                     <l>There thou muſt lodge to night with ſome-body.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>That was a boding word. But <hi>Paranymph</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou haſt a <hi>Epithalamium?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <p>Quick then let's hear't: I long till ſhe's abed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Joy to the Bride, whom now you ſee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Like to the Iſle of</hi> Sicilie:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which round about the Ocean laves,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And gently courts with chryſtal waves:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which purling in white foam, may be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In Tipe, the Zone of Chaſtity:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Come hither, watry Nymphs, and chide,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The ſlower pace, of our fair Bride:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Come clearer Rivers, Brooks, and Springs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Behold, and envy what ſhe brings:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Far purer thoughts, than are your ſtreams,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By the reflection of Heavens beams:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Come Bridegroom, come, and happy be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With thy fair Iſle of</hi> Cecilie.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>'Tis</hi> Hymen <hi>calls, come tie the Band;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Joyn with this Iſle of ſever'd land:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That with a mutual, free conſent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You both, may make one continent.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>I, that's the way to live honeſt: now you <hi>Pronuba?</hi> ne're a wiſe word?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:199600:24"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes my Lord.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Long may the Bride and Bridegroom joy, and I Be next to ſhare in like felicity.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Daughter, here we leave you, ſo good night —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <p>This will be good, I know twas ſuch to me.
<stage>Exeunt. Manet Cecilie.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Aſſiſt me Heaven! — Here on my Chamber Door.</l>
                     <l>I fix this ſacred ſpell, to force from hence</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Valerian:</hi> 'gainſt which if he reſiſt,
<stage>Hangs up the Copy of Verſes.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Heaven has a ſtronger Guard. —
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Anguſta, Tiburtius.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Here my Lord, here you may freely paſs</l>
                     <l>Unto her Chamber; ſo I leave you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>Do ſo.</l>
                     <l>Hum! what have we here? a paper pendant?</l>
                     <l>She's muſical, and by a Sonnet may</l>
                     <l>Rather invite me, than by word of mouth. —</l>
                     <l>Being ſo modeſt as ſhe is —
<stage>He reads.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <q>
                     <l>Back, back <hi>Valerian,</hi> hence, away:</l>
                     <l>Such bold attempts, muſt have delay.</l>
                     <l>Here's no ſafety to be found,</l>
                     <l>Back, away; 'tis ſacred ground,</l>
                     <l>Where a Champion by my ſide,</l>
                     <l>Stands to guard me as his Bride.</l>
                     <l>Back, back <hi>Valerian,</hi> hence, away;</l>
                     <l>Such bold attempts, muſt have delay.</l>
                  </q>
                  <l>Back <hi>Valerian?</hi> as much to ſay, as</l>
                  <l>Come <hi>Tiburtius.</hi> But there's a Champion</l>
                  <l>Within (ſhe ſays) which guards her as a Bride.</l>
                  <l>What Paramour? what Rival's this? why ſhould</l>
                  <l>I hazard life? No, let <hi>Valerian</hi> come,</l>
                  <l>To grapple with th' Antagoniſt: who ſlain,</l>
                  <l>She will abhor my brother for the fact.</l>
                  <l>But ſay <hi>Valerian</hi> ſhould be ſlain? what then?</l>
                  <l>I have th' eſtate, and powerful riches move,</l>
                  <l>And is the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> to Love.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:199600:25"/>
                  <head>Scene <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>The Coaſt is clear, no lurking Pyrate lies</l>
                     <l>In wait, no Shelf, nor Rock, nor Quickſand here;</l>
                     <l>That threatens Shipwrack to my fraighted Bark,</l>
                     <l>That's bound for <hi>Cecilie:</hi> I'le put to ſhore.</l>
                     <l>Yet ſtay: what have we here ſixt on her Door?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Back, back,</hi> Valerian, <hi>hence, away;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What means this Charm? or what infernal Spell</l>
                     <l>Is this which ſo conjures <hi>Valerian?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Here's no ſafety to be found.</hi> I am betraid</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where a Champion by my ſide,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Stands to guard me as his Bride?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hum! be what he will, <hi>Hector</hi> or <hi>Hercules;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I dare encounter, <hi>Back, back,</hi> Valerian? No.</l>
                     <stage>Valerian <hi>pulls the Curtain and</hi> Cecilie <hi>enters.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Lady this traverſe muſt no longer, be,</l>
                     <l>Partition to our Loves, who are as one.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>I come my Lord, why are you thus incens'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Come then, and let me like the amorous vine</l>
                     <l>About the Elm, enfold thee in mine Armes.</l>
                     <l>Nay flie not back, maugre thy Magick Spels,</l>
                     <l>Champion or Devil, Ile not be retrograde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>Keep off, <hi>Valerian,</hi> touch me not, or die.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>The intereſt I claim is due by promiſe,</l>
                     <l>And ratifi'd by Heaven: th' art mine: I muſt</l>
                     <l>And will enjoy thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay good my Lord,</l>
                     <l>But hear me ſpeak.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! Noble Sir,</l>
                     <l>Be not too raſh: Condemn me not before</l>
                     <l>You know me guilty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak then, but be ſuccinct.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>I will, and thus a ſecret do unfold.</l>
                     <l>There is an Angel Guardian of my ſoul</l>
                     <l>And body too. A glorious powerful wight,</l>
                     <l>Brighter than <hi>Phaebus</hi> rayes, when he with all</l>
                     <l>His luſtre darts his fiery-ſprakling beams.</l>
                     <l>Whoſe eye like burning lamps reſplendent ſhine.</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199600:25"/>
                     <l>Whoſe Arms can reach above <hi>Olympus</hi> height.</l>
                     <l>Whoſe breath can blaſt, as Northern winds do buds,</l>
                     <l>An hoaſt of warriers. Dwarfs your Giants were</l>
                     <l>That fought againſt your Gods, compar'd with him,</l>
                     <l>Nay more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, you have ſaid enough: too much,</l>
                     <l>Beyond belief. But think not thus to ſcare</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Valerian</hi> with your bugbears. There within</l>
                     <l>Thy Chamber, thou falſe-hearted <hi>Cecily,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy Paramour lurks, whom, that he may eſcape,</l>
                     <l>Thou mak'ſt ſo terrible. Tuſh! I nor fear</l>
                     <l>His dreadful brow, nor more than humane ſtrength.</l>
                     <l>This ſword ſhall make a paſſage through his heart:</l>
                     <l>VVhere ſhould I finde thee, oh! Could my juſt wrath</l>
                     <l>Forbear to quell what moſt I lov'd till now.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>And may do ſtill my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Say then, what is he?</l>
                     <l>But I muſt ſee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſhall, but if you now,</l>
                     <l>Now as you are a <hi>Pagan,</hi> ſhould attempt</l>
                     <l>To violate by force, He, though unſeen,</l>
                     <l>Will ſtrike you dead. Which miſchief to prevent,</l>
                     <l>I beg upon my knees you will forbear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>May I not ſee him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>He's a Spirit, Sir,</l>
                     <l>Has no Corporeal ſubſtance, can aſſume</l>
                     <l>A ſhape ſo dreadfull, As no mortal can Behold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>All this is but illuſion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>Then, cauſe you'r jealous, ſearch my Chamber round.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>I will.
<stage>Val. <hi>ſearches within.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay look in every corner, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>I have, and no man finde. Why then th'art chaſte</l>
                     <l>And true to thy <hi>Valerian:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven knows I am.</l>
                     <l>And love you 'bove all mortals. Therefore I</l>
                     <l>Beg on my knees with tears, not to attempt</l>
                     <l>To bring me to your Bed, and haſten fate,</l>
                     <l>Which brings a double death: That of your ſoul:</l>
                     <l>'Tis that my Lord, which makes mine eyes diſtill</l>
                     <l>Theſe dewy drops, which trickling down my cheeks</l>
                     <l>From thence aſcend to the Almighty's throne,</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:199600:26"/>
                     <l>To beg of him t'appeaſe and curb your wrath,</l>
                     <l>And to couſtrain your too much daring hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt preval'd but 'tis on this condition</l>
                     <l>That I may ſee that Angel; and I vow.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Vow to believe, and joyn with me in faith.</l>
                     <l>Then ſhall our ſouls be linkt, our loves more chaſte;</l>
                     <l>And if I ſhew you not that glorious wight,</l>
                     <l>Say, I am falſe, and my Religion ſuch:</l>
                     <l>Say I am treacherous both to Heaven and you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>I could be curious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Be not ſo my Lord,</l>
                     <l>But really proceed, and with deſire,</l>
                     <l>Of Heaven, which muſt be priz'd above a wife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I am reſolv'd; what then muſt next be done?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>VVill you be ſecret?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>As thyne own heart my Dear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>In <hi>Via Appia,</hi> which your Lordſhip knows,</l>
                     <l>Not far from hence, in Vaults within the Earth,</l>
                     <l>Lye many Chriſtians. 'Mongſt the reſt there's one,</l>
                     <l>A venerable Man, <hi>our holy Biſhop,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be pleas'd (attended by my man) to go</l>
                     <l>To him, who will inſtruct you in our Faith:</l>
                     <l>And when the purifying ſtreams ſhall rinſe,</l>
                     <l>And cleanſe the Ordures of your tainted ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Return to me: and then you ſhall behold,</l>
                     <l>What, next th' eternal power, is wonderfull.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Methinks a light's transfu'sd into my ſoul,</l>
                     <l>And a more powerfull fire has ſeiz'd upon</l>
                     <l>My now relenting heart, which do's adde wings</l>
                     <l>To my deſires, Madam, I take my leave:</l>
                     <l>Till my return, be what you are.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Still yours.—</l>
                     <l>'Tis but the hand of Heaven which wounding cures.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Tiburtius.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>Hum! my brother gone, and not ſo much as blood ſhed?</l>
                     <l>This kill-cow Champion then enjoys her ſtill.
<stage>Cecily ſings within.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Liſt, ſhe's in triumph, ſinging, and now 'tis</l>
                     <l>Back back <hi>Tiburtius.</hi> Fear not; I am not ſo forward</l>
                     <l>To hazard life or limb for a Miſtris:</l>
                     <l>Mach leſs for thee who haſt a Paramour.</l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:199600:26"/>
                     <l>Expect not then <hi>Tiburtius</hi> bold attempt.—</l>
                     <l>Yet, Madam! madam!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>VVhat's he diſturbs us there?</l>
                     <l>Is't you my Lord <hi>Tiburtius?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>As you ſee.</l>
                     <l>But where's <hi>Valerian</hi> your Lord and Love? ſcar'd hence</l>
                     <l>By your ſo dreadfull Champion, or your ſpells?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Not ſo, but to return again he's gone.</l>
                     <l>And when they meet by one ſole interview,</l>
                     <l>All quarrels ſhall be ended.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>Very good.</l>
                     <l>And who of three ſhall then enjoy your love?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>That ſoon ſhall be diſcover'd by th'event.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet one thing ere we part, I fain would know:</l>
                     <l>By what Enchantment now, while VVinter cloathes</l>
                     <l>The Earth with ſnow and hoary froſts, ſuch odours</l>
                     <l>Breath, as if with rich perfume the Lilly</l>
                     <l>And ſweeter Roſe were by a forward Spring,</l>
                     <l>Brought forth to yield their pleaſing ſavours, here;</l>
                     <l>No Flowers I ſee, but Roſes in your Cheeks,</l>
                     <l>No Lillies, but thoſe Ivory fingers there,</l>
                     <l>VVhich cannot vent ſuch odoriferous ſents,</l>
                     <l>As now perfume the Ayre.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Noble Sir,</l>
                     <l>Think not, we Chriſtians work by Magick art.—</l>
                     <l>VVith Roſes here, and Lillies intermixt</l>
                     <l>My temples with a Coronet are wreath'd,</l>
                     <l>VVhich though you ſee not, we no Sorcery</l>
                     <l>Have us'd to blinde your eyes, which have a filme</l>
                     <l>That overſpreads your ſight. Go, go, my Lord;</l>
                     <l>I pray go to your brother, take his advice;</l>
                     <l>And then return: then (happy) ſhall you ſee,</l>
                     <l>The Garland which I wear of fragrant Flowers;</l>
                     <l>And ſee beſides with him, what I have promis'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, your Charm is powerfull; I'le away.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>May Heaven illumine both as he begins,</l>
                     <l>And born again ſhall be theſe Noble Twins.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:199600:27"/>
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Almachius, Saphricius, <hi>Officers, and Headſman with an Axe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>COme bring him forth, I'le ſee the Execution;</l>
                     <l>Or if he yet relent and ſacrifice</l>
                     <l>Unto our gods, he's pardon'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>To your gods?</l>
                     <l>Your Devils, Monſters, Moppets, Puppets, Bugges.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Out thou blaſphemous wretch! away with him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>I have endur'd a torture in each joynt:</l>
                     <l>Theſe feet were ſcorch'd, theſe arms with burning torches:</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Nicephorus.</stage>
                     <l>Yet could I ſuffer more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Take him away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>O! let me come; 'tis more than time to ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Saphricius! Saphricius!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>What's hee</l>
                     <l>That interrupts our Juſtice?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Saphricius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I once was thy dear friend, and thou we'rt mine,</l>
                     <l>Untill (unfortunate) we fell at jarres,</l>
                     <l>And open enmity, yet now at leaſt</l>
                     <l>Forgive, as I do thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Forgive thee? no.</l>
                     <l>Thou too injurious wer't to be forgiven.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>Say all the fault were mine, and only you</l>
                     <l>Were injur'd, yet now deſtin'd as a Victim</l>
                     <l>And ſacrifice for Heaven, what Heaven commands</l>
                     <l>For Heaven's ſake do not omit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>I never will forgive thee.</l>
                     <l>He troubles me here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p>Come Sirrah, ſtand aſide.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <p>Pardon; upon my knees I beg it; forgive me Good <hi>Saphricius.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <l>What an abſurd fellow art thou?</l>
                     <l>VVhat need'ſt fear him, he's going to die.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:199600:27"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh there's a Power above; all Charity,</l>
                     <l>All Goodneſs, Love; for which he gives his life,</l>
                     <l>To which his ſoul relates, and muſt be like,</l>
                     <l>In rendring good for ill, and pardoning all:</l>
                     <l>Therefore upon my knees, again I beg it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Away thou hatefull and injurious man,</l>
                     <l>Nor I, nor Heaven, will pardon thy offence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>Here proſtrate on the earth, I kiſs your feet,</l>
                     <l>Though you likewiſe I thought had wronged me;</l>
                     <l>Yet be the fault all mine, forgive me, Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I: this fellow vexes me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p>Be gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alma.</speaker>
                     <p>Force him to ſilence there, or ſtop his mouth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p>Now prepare: y'are come to th' place aſſign'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>Aſſign'd for what?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <l>For Death, by this keen Axe.</l>
                     <l>Becauſe thou wilt not offer ſacrifice</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Jupiter;</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>So, is't for that cauſe, then—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Executioner do your Office.
<stage>Saphr. trembles.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <l>I will my Lord</l>
                     <l>Inſtantly. The valiant <hi>Saphricius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who late endur'd all kinde of Tortures, now</l>
                     <l>Begins to tremble every joynt and limbe.</l>
                     <l>I'le cure him of his Palſey.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold, ah! hold</l>
                     <l>Thy hand, my friend, and hear one word.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <l>What's that?</l>
                     <l>For two thou ſhalt not have, what is it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>Gods.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak that again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Unto the Gods I ſay,</l>
                     <l>I'le ſacrifice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhat ſays he there, of Gods?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Off.</speaker>
                     <p>That he to them will ſacrifice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <l>Diſcover</l>
                     <l>Too I will, what now a Chriſtian Lady</l>
                     <l>Is perpetrating 'gainſt two Noble Lords.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou haſt thy life: The gods are mercifull,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord! my Name's <hi>Nicephorus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>What's next?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <p>I am a Chriſtian too, and what this Renegade</p>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:199600:28"/>
                     <l>Has loſt, I come to gain; a Palm of Victory.</l>
                     <l>A Crown immortall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Art thou then a Chriſtian?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſay, I am; and were it poſſible</l>
                     <l>VVould give another life, ſo that I might</l>
                     <l>Reclaym him there who has renounc'd his Faith</l>
                     <l>For want of Love: the badge a Martyr brings,</l>
                     <l>Elſe cannot have the honour to be ſuch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Gaoler, take him to your cuſtody. And to morrow</l>
                     <l>(If he recant not, as his fellow has done)</l>
                     <l>Executioner you know your Office, let him dye.</l>
                     <l>I muſt away: affairs which much import</l>
                     <l>Are calling on me. Come <hi>Saphricius</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I go to offer Incenſe to great <hi>Jove;</hi>
                        <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sap.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le joyn with you my Lord moſt willingly.
<stage>
                           <hi>Manet</hi> Niceph. <hi>&amp; Execut.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                     <l>He's gone; O miſerable man! he's loſt</l>
                     <l>For ever loſt, I fear. Suffer'd ſo much?</l>
                     <l>So long! and at the laſt apoſtatize.— ay me!</l>
                     <l>Have you not well obſerv'd the Provence Roſe,</l>
                     <l>How every leaf pluckt from the Neighbouring Chives,</l>
                     <l>Is tipt as 'twere with Gold? Such are our actions,</l>
                     <l>Such our thoughts; when golden Charity</l>
                     <l>And Love dos guild our every leavy thought,</l>
                     <l>Sprung from the ſoul: elſe nought avails, nor death,</l>
                     <l>Without the hearty love of friend and Foe:</l>
                     <l>He onely dyeth well, that's living ſo.—
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>Valerian <hi>and</hi> Tiburtius <hi>come out of the Vault,</hi> Urban <hi>appearing to the middle above the Vault.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Urban.</speaker>
                     <l>MY Lord <hi>Valerian</hi> (twice the elder Son</l>
                     <l>By birth and Faith) you'l have a ſpecial care</l>
                     <l>Of him that ſeconds you, your only brother,</l>
                     <l>Who leſs inſtructed, cauſe the time was ſhort,</l>
                     <l>Next that of Heaven t'aſſiſt, wants your ſuppport.—</l>
                     <l>You are my children now, and ſheep: farewell.</l>
                     <l>Doubt not the Lady wil fulfill her word.</l>
                     <l>Remember now y'are Combatants for Heaven:</l>
                     <l>And that your Guerdon, an immortal Crown,</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:199600:28"/>
                     <l>Is that you fight for; not for fading wreathes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>For this Atchievement we entreat your Prayers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Urban.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor I in that, nor in paternal care</l>
                     <l>Will be defective, Heaven bleſs my Children.
<stage>Deſcends.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Where we have been, what ſeen, and what acquir'd;</l>
                     <l>Our breſts may better lodge than we can utter.</l>
                     <l>W'have been in Paradiſe, beheld a Heaven</l>
                     <l>I'th bowels of the earth: the Chriſtian Flock</l>
                     <l>Within a Fold, whoſe darkneſs is exil'd,</l>
                     <l>As well b' exemplar life, as burning Lamps.</l>
                     <l>Here ſome in Prayers, there others chaunting Hymns.</l>
                     <l>Here ſome in Contemplation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>Others I ſaw</l>
                     <l>And heard exhorting to a vertuous life,</l>
                     <l>And ſome inſtructing <hi>Catechumens,</hi> ſuch</l>
                     <l>As prepare themſelves for holy tincture.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Not mine and thine is heard amongſt them there,</l>
                     <l>But all in common, all one heart, one will:</l>
                     <l>Unanimous they live. VVhy now methinks</l>
                     <l>I am arm'd 'gainſt all events.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le follow you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Could pull down Idols, and deſtroy their Fanes:</l>
                     <l>O! what a greeting will there be betwixt</l>
                     <l>That vertuous Lady and our new born ſelves?</l>
                     <stage>Enter Three Watchmen.</stage>
                     <l>Madam I come, I flye with wings of Love,</l>
                     <l>One ſoul with thine, one heart and faith I bring,</l>
                     <l>Now touch thy Organ, and melodious ſing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>But heark, my Lord, ere we ſet forward,—</l>
                     <l>I am deceiv'd if I ſee not ſome here in <hi>Via Appia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are wont to lie in wait for Chriſtians.</l>
                     <l>1. Come my Maſters, keep your ſtanding.</l>
                     <l>2. I ſee two of 'hem.</l>
                     <l>3. Then let's comprehend 'hem.</l>
                     <l>1. No, we'le reſpect 'hem till they come within</l>
                     <l>Reach, and then down with 'hem.</l>
                     <l>2. No, no, let's dog 'hem home, and beſet the houſe.</l>
                     <l>3. That we may do by the ſent; for I ſmell them already,</l>
                     <l>Th' are ſo muskifyed;</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:199600:29"/>
                     <l>1. I follow 'hem cloſe. So, ſo, when they're hous'd Have at 'hem, then, hah for a Booty.
<stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE V.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Flavia, <hi>and</hi> Marcus, Anguſta, Metricio, Phantaſio, Palinodio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <p>A <hi>Nguſtula,</hi> come ye hither.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <p>Tell me, when was your Ladie's bed laſt made?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, upon the Marriage day i'th morning</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <p>And never ſmce?
<stage>Mar. <hi>looks within.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſince indeed, Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis even ſo: Nay worſe, for 'tis yet made.</l>
                     <l>Ay me! here's no body. Ah! that bodeing! ſomebody</l>
                     <l>Has deceiv'd us VVife. This a Nuptial bed?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, not ſo much as tumbled on.
<stage>VVhy where?</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhere lay my Daughter all this while.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas!</l>
                     <l>Good Lady! if he came not to bed, was't</l>
                     <l>Her fault? In former times (I know it well)</l>
                     <l>She often watch'd all night: ſpent it in prayer:</l>
                     <l>But now what Lady could have been ſo godly?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <p>I am vext.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo am I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay I am</l>
                     <l>Aſham'd to ſee't, wed and not bed together!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>Now Sir, you with your Epithalamiums,
<stage>To Met.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your Epigrams, Anagrams, Chronograms,</l>
                     <l>Your Raptures, Enthuſiaſmes, and Whim-whams.</l>
                     <l>To humour my Daughter, with your Melancholy</l>
                     <l>Strains, that now ſhe's fit for no-thing, nor no-</l>
                     <l>-Body, that I ſee; And you with your <hi>Dia-</hi>
                        <stage>To Phan.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>-<hi>Paſons,</hi> and brain-ſick Crotchets! you have run</l>
                     <l>A fair diviſion, have you not, to ſeparate</l>
                     <l>Man and VVife? And you Gentleman-uſher.
<stage>To Pal.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>That look ſo wilde: you that have been rambling—</l>
                     <l>And now come ſcar'd out of your little wits,</l>
                     <l>VVhat newes? what's the matter with you now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:199600:29"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>A matter of matters, nay all my back and ſides</l>
                     <l>Had been <hi>Matter,</hi> but that Noble <hi>Tiburtius</hi> came</l>
                     <l>To ſuccour me. Otherwiſe I had been ſtript and whipt,</l>
                     <l>Onely for ſaying my Lady was as fair as <hi>Venus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>But where's my Lord <hi>Valerian?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>He'le be here</l>
                     <l>This night, or to morrow morning.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>To morrow morning, will</l>
                     <l>That be a fit time to viſit his wife, Goodman <hi>Pali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodie?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then to Night Madam, he'le be here.
<stage>money Both give him Exeunt Mar. &amp; Fla.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou'rt welcome then, here's thy reward. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>And here; come <hi>Flavia</hi> let's prepare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Poet and Muſitian, look here.<note n="†" place="margin">Shews the money.</note> Will you participate? No.</l>
                     <l>'Tis ſtrange a Poet that ſtands ſo much on feet,</l>
                     <l>Should fall into wants: Or that a Muſitian</l>
                     <l>Should not live as well on good aires, as a Sycophant</l>
                     <l>By an ill breath; but nothing ſtrange that this</l>
                     <l>Gentleman-Uſher<note n="†" place="margin">Kiſſes his hand, and congies.</note> by this, and this, is richly clad</l>
                     <l>In pluſh here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <p>So, ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet that you may not ſing with heavy heart</l>
                     <l>For both your Muſes, go, I have a quart.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>ACT. V. Scene 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Valerian.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>FEar, with belief, unpowers: diſarmes me now</l>
                     <l>Who late was daring, while (an unbeliever;)</l>
                     <l>I could not credit what by faith I've learn'd,</l>
                     <l>That there are Spirits call'd Intelligences,</l>
                     <l>On whoſe Majeſtick brow a terrour dwells. —</l>
                     <l>The gentle plaites I dare not now unfold,</l>
                     <l>Who once could like a violent torrent ruſh</l>
                     <l>Into her Chamber. Might I ſee Her firſt,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe countenance is angelical, from thence</l>
                     <l>Mine eye might be transferr'd, though fearfully</l>
                     <l>To view her Angel.
<stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Devil.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:199600:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dev.</speaker>
                     <l>Here I am: look then,</l>
                     <l>On me; an Angel.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>But not hers, thou art</l>
                     <l>So monſtrous, ugly, and deform'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dev.</speaker>
                     <l>I am.</l>
                     <l>And that I may evict belief from thee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note n="†" place="margin">A Maſque of Ladies, Devils &amp; Satyrs. The Dance ended, when <hi>Valerian</hi> draws the Curtain, they all vaniſh, and <hi>Cecilie</hi> enter.</note>See Nymphs and Ladies here which I command,</l>
                     <l>As fair as thine: Mine rather might have ſaid,</l>
                     <l>For when ſhe's ſlumbring in her bed, I ſtand</l>
                     <l>And gently fold in mine, her lilly hand.</l>
                     <l>Which nimbly now ſhall touch the Organ: and,</l>
                     <l>While that, and other Muſick ſounds; t'advance</l>
                     <l>The power I have, I here command a Dance.
<stage>They dance.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Cecilie.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Welcome my Lord, my deareſt Love and Spouſe.</l>
                     <l>What means this ghaſtly look? what is't you fear?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>They're vaniſh'd all with him, who ſtanding there</l>
                     <l>Told me, he was thine Angel; but ſo ugly,</l>
                     <l>I could not think a beauty had commerce</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a monſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>No; my Lord, 'twas he</l>
                     <l>Who oppoſite to my bleſt Guardian, ſeeks</l>
                     <l>To ruin that, the other do's preſerve.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>But here were Ladies too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>But airy Phantoſmes:</l>
                     <l>Deluding Devils, they who can aſſume</l>
                     <l>What ſhape they liſt: yet ſtill are limited</l>
                     <l>In that, and power by the Almighty's will</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>And yours it ſeems; for at th' approach of day,</l>
                     <l>As the black <hi>Negra</hi> Night with Ravens wings</l>
                     <l>Poſts from the Confines of the Univerſe,</l>
                     <l>So did at your aſpect, theſe ſpirits vaniſh. —

<stage>Enter Angel with two wreaths of flowers, made of Lilies and Roſes.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord, I need not be inquiſitive to know</l>
                     <l>What now you are: this object ſhall ſuffice</l>
                     <l>To tell how faith has clear'd your gloomy eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>But not ſo eagle-ſighted yet am I</l>
                     <l>As to behold this glorious wight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet, but</l>
                     <l>A ray, or glimpſe of the immortal power.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:199600:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Angel.</speaker>
                     <l>Hail to you Virgin, and your happy Spouſe,</l>
                     <l>Bleſt be your Loves, which heaven has linkt in one.</l>
                     <l>I come from you bright Manſion, Paradice;</l>
                     <l>From thence have brought theſe fragrant wreaths of flowers</l>
                     <l>The pure white Lilly and the crimſon Roſe</l>
                     <l>That, to denote your ſpotleſs, chaſter Loves;</l>
                     <l>This, to preſent the ardour of your flames,</l>
                     <l>Which upward tend towards th' immortal fire.</l>
                     <l>Bow, bow yourheads, while croſſe-wiſe thus I crown,</l>
                     <l>To ſymbolize, you muſt ſtoop low to riſe.</l>
                     <l>And like the Palme be preſt; for with renown,</l>
                     <l>Without Afflictions Croſſe, is gain'd no Crown.
<stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Tiburtius <hi>and kneels.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <l>Here yet a Crown expects a Champions head,</l>
                  <l>Who in his firſt (as he was born from Earth)</l>
                  <l>Come's now to joyn, bleſt by a ſecond birth.</l>
                  <l>Joyn Arm in Arm as you enwombed lay,
<stage>The brothers embrace.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>A loving pair, yet happier twins too day.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Cecilie</hi> ſings.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So from the Brook return the bathed Doves,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>while from your candid breaſt ſpring purer Loves.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So from the waters waſhd, we may behold</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The pure white ſheep return unto the fold,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So in the dewy Morn, we ſee the Larkes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So fraighted come a pair of wave-waſh'd Barkes.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then welcome Doves with chaſter Loves.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Welcome enroll'd Sheep in the fold,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mount pair of Larkes, and for your Barkes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heaven be your Haven: ne're disband,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Here caſt your Anchor, Hope; and Land.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Angel</speaker>
                     <l>Time calls away to mount bove liquid skies,</l>
                     <l>Be arm'd, prepare, a ſudden ſtorm will riſe</l>
                     <l>Loſe not your Sea-mark Heaven, but boldlyſteer.—</l>
                     <l>The Tempeſt paſt, dark clouds ſhall diſappear;</l>
                     <l>Next, Day eternal ſhine; Bleſt three adieu,—</l>
                     <l>None ſhall behold your wreatths, but ſuch as you.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Come then Diſaſters, Fire, and Sword, and Racks.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>Come what can come, what ſpiteful hell can belch,</l>
                     <l>Or Heaven ſhall pleaſe to ſend, or ſhall permit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:199600:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Or come whatſoe're it be, as we embrace,</l>
                     <l>We'le hug their torments. What is't once to die,</l>
                     <l>To live ſo many lives, eternally?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>My dear <hi>Valerian,</hi> now, as fully mine,</l>
                     <l>As I am yours, and both linkt to a third,</l>
                     <l>Your deareſt brother: ſummon'd now by heaven</l>
                     <l>To be ingulf'd in a tempeſtuous Mayne,</l>
                     <l>Let's to his Standard flie, who now invites</l>
                     <l>His ſouldiers to a Combate. His pure-white</l>
                     <l>Of Innocence, and flowing purple, tells,</l>
                     <l>Ours muſt be like, although no parallels.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Almachius, <hi>and Officers,</hi> Maximus <hi>and Attendants.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Off.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>There my Lord; thoſe two we dog'd from <hi>Via Appia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Valerian</hi> and <hi>Tiburtius</hi> Chriſtians? I thought as much.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>But not ſo much as we can act of Chriſtians.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor could I think ſo much of Sorcery,</l>
                     <l>As can this younger Lady actuate:</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Marcus <hi>and</hi> Flavia.</stage>
                     <l>Lay hold of her and thoſe her two Diſciples.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhat have we here to do? Diſturb me in My own houſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>And carry hence your Daughter too,</l>
                     <l>That's more; for Juſtice has no limit. Take her Away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>It ſhall not need my Lord: I paſſe</l>
                     <l>My word, ſhe ſhall be forth coming.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay here,</l>
                     <l>Your houſe is ample, we can ſoon diſpatch.</l>
                     <l>Let firſt the Brothers come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>VVe rather flie,</l>
                     <l>T'embrace the worſt of deaths thou canſt invent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Y'are Noble; adore our mighty Gods, and live.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>That were t'offend th' Almighty Power of Heaven.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>You know the penalty, to loſe your goods, Confiſcate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Goods? They are but breeding evils:</l>
                     <l>But now disburs'd amongſt the poor, a treaſure laid up in Heaven.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:199600:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>I there ſhe ſtands who Wrought this policy,</l>
                     <l>VVe'l come to hear the fource of all this miſchief.</l>
                     <l>Mean while (my Lords) you (to reſolve) retire,</l>
                     <l>Either t'adore the Gods, or be beheaded.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>VVhat two extreams are theſe? Or make a Stock</l>
                     <l>Or Stone a God (renouncing him above,</l>
                     <l>t'incur everlaſting death) or die.</l>
                     <l>This I. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>And I embrace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>To die but once.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>Live ever: Thus I am reſolv'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>And I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Then take 'hem hence.
<stage>Exeunt Val. &amp; Tib.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Bring in the Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Offic.</speaker>
                     <p>She's here my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sitting down.] Cecile,</hi> thou art here arraign'd for hainous crimes,</l>
                     <l>Which who could think were lurking in a breaſt</l>
                     <l>So young and tender? In a Damoſel fair,</l>
                     <l>And by extraction Noble? But when Vice</l>
                     <l>Uſurpes a hold in better Natures, ſoon</l>
                     <l>They are deprav'd, like richer wines, which once,</l>
                     <l>Corrupted, taint the Veſſel more where th' are</l>
                     <l>Enclos'd—So young! yet could'ſt by Magick Art</l>
                     <l>Enchaunt the Lord <hi>Valerian;</hi> who enamour'd,</l>
                     <l>Was by thy powerful and bewitching charmes</l>
                     <l>Bound in the chains of a prodigious love. —</l>
                     <l>Then was he wrought upon t'abjure the Gods,</l>
                     <l>And march among the ſuperſtitious rank</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch Impoſtors as thy ſelf. — This done,</l>
                     <l>(For miſchief has no period) you engroſs</l>
                     <l>His Goods, his Plate, and Jewels: Was content</l>
                     <l>To feign a Marriage, more t'endear your ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Though 'twere by proſtitution. Next you were content</l>
                     <l>He might be publickly traduc'd</l>
                     <l>For Chriſtianiſme, and now to loſe his head,</l>
                     <l>With his, as Noble Brother, Lord <hi>Tiburtius.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVho elſe might have enjoy'd his full eſtate.</l>
                     <l>Laſtly, to cheat the Emperour of his Right,</l>
                     <l>VVhich comes for want of heir, they have I ſee,</l>
                     <l>VVhich was a plot of yours) they have no place,</l>
                     <l>No other Magazine (where they have hid</l>
                     <l>Their treaſure) but Beggars, Rogues, and Raſcals,</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:199600:32"/>
                     <l>Apoſtates, and ſuch like ſcum of th' earth. —</l>
                     <l>All's gone, all given away, by which you hope</l>
                     <l>(Forſooth) to gratifie your poor-born God.</l>
                     <l>Is not this true, and verified by many</l>
                     <l>Which I could name; amongſt the reſt <hi>Saphricius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A holy Convert, who was one of yours,</l>
                     <l>Well vers'd in all your plots. But why ſhould I</l>
                     <l>Exaggerate, what of it ſelf is ſo,</l>
                     <l>Enormous? No: I pity Lady your</l>
                     <l>More tender years, and Noble Parents here:</l>
                     <l>Pity a beauty which deſerves to be</l>
                     <l>Enthron'd upon a Princely Seat, rather</l>
                     <l>Than be ſo vilified, and made ſo baſe</l>
                     <l>As to conſort with ſordid, deſpicable,</l>
                     <l>And abject riff-raffe, vipers, vermines, worms,</l>
                     <l>Which creep in th' earth, and lurk in horrid Caves.</l>
                     <l>What ſay you Lady, deny? or guilty yield?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>What need I traverſe this Indictment? all</l>
                     <l>Compacted of untruths? know then I am</l>
                     <l>A Chriſtian; not therefore baſe; but you</l>
                     <l>Who in your Gods, do homage to the Devil.</l>
                     <l>Chriſtian and baſe! O! had I breath enough,</l>
                     <l>To eccho in the air this glorious Name!</l>
                     <l>A title 'tis; <hi>Encomium,</hi> that tranſcends</l>
                     <l>'Bove humane things; by Chriſtian I am made.</l>
                     <l>More noble than by birth, more powerful than</l>
                     <l>Your <hi>Caeſars;</hi> more victorious. Tell me of Goods?</l>
                     <l>Gold, Plate, and Jewels! Theſe I more contemn,</l>
                     <l>Than what I trample on. Unworthy Judge</l>
                     <l>That call'ſt me proſtitute, I defie</l>
                     <l>Thee, and thy Goddeſſes, that were but ſuch:</l>
                     <l>Harlots, and Queans: thy Gods adulterous. <hi>Va'erian</hi> is my Spouſe; but far more dear</l>
                     <l>By that which now he is: A Chriſtian.</l>
                     <l>This our glory, this is our true renown,</l>
                     <l>To gain by combate an immortal Crown.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Our patience is abus'd, our Gods contemn'd,</l>
                     <l>To whom, or ſacrifice, or die.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>But die?</l>
                     <l>Die but one death? muſt I but loſe one life</l>
                     <l>To purchaſe an eternal? Oh! how good!</l>
                     <l>How bounteous heaven, which by a quick return,</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:199600:32"/>
                     <l>Renders for death a life for ever happy!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Bring 'hem forth there; Sha't ſee to what thou'ſt brought</l>
                     <l>A wretched pair, who late were Noble Lords.
<stage>
                           <hi>Enter Headſman</hi> Val. <hi>and</hi> Tib. <hi>and</hi> Cec.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>And if good Nature be not utterly</l>
                     <l>In thee deprav'd, thy more relenting heart</l>
                     <l>Cannot but have remorſe. See here they come.</l>
                     <l>Poor Lords? dejected men! that fix on thee</l>
                     <l>Their heavy eyes, from whence the miſchief ſprang.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Not heavy eyes, not ſad, but chearful, clear;</l>
                     <l>Made ſuch by the reflexive light of heaven.</l>
                     <l>My Lords, you my dear Spouſe, and you his brother.</l>
                     <l>You have th' honour firſt t'inveſt your ſelves</l>
                     <l>Within the liſts, where I ſhould firſt have been,</l>
                     <l>Who firſt ſhew'd you the way: but y'have out-ſtript</l>
                     <l>Your Leader as leſſe worthy, who ſhall be</l>
                     <l>Happier to trace the manly ſteps you tread.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear Spouſe and Miſtriſs (not in <hi>Venus</hi> School,</l>
                     <l>But that of Heaven) by you we firſt were taught</l>
                     <l>A leſſon which we now have got by heart:</l>
                     <l>That humane love is like a coal of fire,</l>
                     <l>Which lies on th' hearth; but by the mounting flame</l>
                     <l>A love divine is figur'd, which tranſcends.</l>
                     <l>Therefore ſalute you with a chaſt embrace.</l>
                     <l>Farewel dear Spouſe.
<stage>Embraces her.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Death parts but for a while,</l>
                     <l>I'le haſten after; that as our bodies bed</l>
                     <l>In earth-together, our ſouls may reunite.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <l>May I be <hi>Paranymph,</hi> and lead the way,</l>
                     <l>Who though I laſt come hither of us two,</l>
                     <l>May by this birth precede.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>O! force of love!</l>
                     <l>Or firſt, or laſt, ambitious in deſire</l>
                     <l>Of heaven, you happy twins ſhall meet again. —</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Lords</hi> you ſuffer here, as <hi>Kings</hi> ſhall reign.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Away with 'hem to th' place of execution.</l>
                     <l>O! now they're coming back, and will recant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear Love adieu.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear Spouſe adieu.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tib.</speaker>
                     <p>We crave your prayers t'aſſiſt us in the way.
<stage>
                           <hi>Exeunt</hi> Val. <hi>and</hi> Tib. <hi>Alm.</hi> Peace</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>Bleſt be your night that brings eternal day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:199600:33"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace, Sorcereſſe, with thy enchaunting tongue.</l>
                     <l>Or ſmoke ſhall ſtop the paſſage of thy breath.</l>
                     <l>Fire ſhall conſume thee Witch; take her away; into her own dry bath.</l>
                     <l>Beſet her round with fagots, and diſſolve</l>
                     <l>To aſhes that polluted corps. Away with her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Thus happy may I be, and loſe my breath,</l>
                     <l>Midſt flames of Love, and die a <hi>Phaenix</hi> death.
<stage>Exit with Officers.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Maximus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Go ſee them beheaded.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>I will, my Lord.
<stage>Exit Max.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Diſpatch and bring me word.
<stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Marcus <hi>and</hi> Flavia <hi>and kneel.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <l>Now my Lord <hi>Marcus,</hi> and my Lady there,</l>
                  <l>What is't you now petition on your knee?</l>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>O! Sorrow, till now, deny'd to give a vent</l>
                     <l>To my ſurcharged ſoul,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>What is't you crave?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>That th' execution of the law may be Suſpended; our Daughter may be reclaim'd, She's young.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>No, no, you ſhould have had a care</l>
                     <l>In time: 'tis now too late, ſhe's ſo poyſon'd
<stage>
                           <hi>Enter</hi> Maximus <hi>looking up in the air, an Officer following.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <l>With Chriſtian ſuperſtition. Now <hi>Maximus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are the two poppy heads cut from their ſtems?</l>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Dead th' are, and yet not dead, ſee where, ſee, ſee, Th' are mounting in the air.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>The fellow's mad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, the glorious ſouls I ſee of that Bleſt pair, <hi>Valerian</hi> and <hi>Tiburtius.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Imaginary Viſions in the air,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe the Twins <hi>Pollux</hi> and <hi>Caſtor,</hi> which</l>
                     <l>We call <hi>Tyndarides.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>No, 'bove the height of the rich ſpangled skies,</l>
                     <l>Two winged Wights, more bright than ſunny beams,</l>
                     <l>I ſee tranſporting of their fulgent ſouls. —</l>
                     <l>Great is <hi>Valerian</hi> and <hi>Tiburtius</hi> God.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet more Witchcraft?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>No, the Gods are Devils,</l>
                     <l>Which have bewitch'd you with their fopperies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Out upon the Villain! blaſphemous Renegade.</l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:199600:33"/>
                     <stage>Enter an Officer.</stage>
                     <l>Take him away to burn with the Enchauntreſſe,</l>
                     <l>If ſhe already be not burn!
<stage>
                           <hi>Exit</hi> Maximus <hi>with Officers.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſman.</speaker>
                     <l>Not burnt my Lord,</l>
                     <l>The flames at diſtance keep, and dare not touch</l>
                     <l>So much as that which doth her body veſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet more ſorcery! why? haſt thou not a ſword</l>
                     <l>To ſever head from ſhoulders?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſman.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes my Lord,</l>
                     <l>Sharp as a razor.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Haſt a vigorous arm?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſm.</speaker>
                     <l>And dextrous too, to ſlice as from the ſtalke,</l>
                     <l>A limber Daſie or a Daffadil. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alm.</speaker>
                     <p>Then come with me, I'le be ſpectator.
<stage>Exeunt Almach. Attendants.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Come <hi>Flavia,</hi> ſhall we not ſee our daughter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Daughter murther'd? Can the loving Ewe</l>
                     <l>Behold her tender lamb ſnatch'd from her ſide,</l>
                     <l>And ſee it ſlaughter'd by the Butchers hand?</l>
                     <l>I cannot husband, be a cruel witneſs</l>
                     <l>Of the diſaſterous death of my dear lamb.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>If flames could not conſume, why ſhould the ſword,</l>
                     <l>Be more injurious to an innocent?</l>
                     <l>Or if her God with a more powerful hand</l>
                     <l>Could curb the raging fire, why may not he</l>
                     <l>Contract the Nerves of that more cruel Butcher?</l>
                     <l>Or arm her Neck againſt the dint of Steel?</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Headſman <hi>looking on his Sword.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>But ſee our hopes are vain: She's dead, ſhe's dead,</l>
                     <l>Behold his murthering Sword beſmear'd with blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſman.</speaker>
                     <l>Hum! what prodigy is this? my Sword's not dull,</l>
                     <l>Nor was my arm bereav'd of wonted ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>Why then, while thrice I ſtruck, and thrice my ſword</l>
                     <l>Had paſſage as I thought 'twixt joynt and joynt;</l>
                     <l>Why fell not down her mown off tottring head?</l>
                     <l>Like ice on cragged rock diſſolv'd by heat?</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Cecilie <hi>lead by her ſervants.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>See here ſhe comes, what ſoder could ſhe have?</l>
                     <l>To cement what this ſword dis joynted thrice</l>
                     <l>Or this is Magick Art, or elſe ſhe has</l>
                     <l>An <hi>Eſculapius</hi> 'bove all power of Gods.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>Lives ſtill our daughter, or by your ſupport</l>
                     <l>Is ſhe but held?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:199600:34"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>Breaths ſtill this virgin head,</l>
                     <l>Which has a languid, yet a ſweet aſpect?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear Parents yet I live, could you believe</l>
                     <l>The fabulous ſtory of your <hi>Hercules,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who ſlic'd off <hi>Hydru</hi>'s heads, which grev again</l>
                     <l>In number moe, yet not believe your eyes,</l>
                     <l>VVhich ſee I live, or ears, which hear me ſpeak?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Still may'ſt thou live, whom now we living ſee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Still would you have me live? Dos't not ſuffice</l>
                     <l>That bounteous heaven has granted me three dayes</l>
                     <l>At my more humble ſuit to intercede</l>
                     <l>For your Converſion?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas what are three dayes</l>
                     <l>To enjoy a Child?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>This was the boon I begg'd,</l>
                     <l>That with your leave, this houſe may be transform'd,</l>
                     <l>And conſecrated to the power above,</l>
                     <l>To be a Church, where true believers may</l>
                     <l>Adore their Maker, and by frequent prayer</l>
                     <l>Appeaſe his wrath, by whoſe permiſſion now</l>
                     <stage>Enter Angel, and ſtands by her.</stage>
                     <l>Th'are perſecuted. — Soft! what whiſpering voice</l>
                     <l>Is that which by prophetick ſpirit tells,</l>
                     <l>That this my body to be buried here,</l>
                     <l>Shall (when a thouſand and four hundred years</l>
                     <l>Are fully paſt and gone) be found entire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>I, Daughter, might we live till then and ſee it.</l>
                     <l>I then would be a Chriſtian.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flae.</speaker>
                     <p>So would I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>You would. Ah! Infidelity! when thou</l>
                     <l>Haſt long been foſtred in a darkſome breaſt,</l>
                     <l>How hard it is for light to be transfus'd;</l>
                     <l>Or heat of love into decrepit age?</l>
                     <l>Happy who young begin to live and love.</l>
                     <l>Dos't hear <hi>Anguſta?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes forſooth Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou weep'ſt I ſee, there can no richer pearls</l>
                     <l>Adde liſtre to a virgins face, than tears</l>
                     <l>VVhich are diſtill'd for expiation of</l>
                     <l>A fin-ſick ſoul. <hi>Tiburtius</hi> thou didſt love;</l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:199600:34"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Valeaian</hi> was my Spouſe. They are gone before</l>
                     <l>T'eternal happineſs. I follow myne.</l>
                     <l>O! may'ſt thou emulate, ſucceed to thyne. <hi>Palinodio.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Here Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou'ſt been</l>
                     <l>But ſtaggering in thy Faith; ſuiting too much</l>
                     <l>VVith <hi>Palinodie,</hi> ready to recant,</l>
                     <l>When but a whipping menac'd to thy skin</l>
                     <l>A tranſitory pain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true, Madam,</l>
                     <l>I never lov'd ſuch tranſitory things,</l>
                     <l>Which by the world entic'd or threaten'd me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou'ſt been my Gentleman-uſher.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes forſooth,</l>
                     <l>I have been ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Henceforth ſhall be no more,</l>
                     <l>To uſher thee to Heaven, I go before. <hi>Metricio.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <p>Here ſweet Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt been</l>
                     <l>My Poet to compoſe in facred Verſe</l>
                     <l>Spiritual Sonnets, ayres that ſuited beſt</l>
                     <l>With th'Organ, my delight at vacant hours.</l>
                     <l>Yet much adoe I had to curb that ſtrain</l>
                     <l>Of levity, thou hadſt, which too propenſe</l>
                     <l>To amorous Ditties, did profuſely vent</l>
                     <l>It ſelf (to pleaſe the humour of the time)</l>
                     <l>In vainer Raptures of Prophaning Love.</l>
                     <l>Deſiſt from this and in a pious way,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſtrayns ſhal raiſe dull thoughts to things on high.</l>
                     <l>Vertue's the ſoul of Verſe not Vanity. <hi>Phantaſio!</hi> my Muſitian, where are you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>Here Madam, I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Inſiſt not much on that.</l>
                     <l>That I, or ſelf-conceit, predominates</l>
                     <l>In thee too much. What is't to have a Voyce</l>
                     <l>To raiſe 'bove <hi>Ela,</hi> while the drooping ſoul</l>
                     <l>Below the baſe of abject things deſcends.</l>
                     <l>Thou tun'ſt mine Organ: Tune thy diſcordant mind</l>
                     <l>Which too phantaſtick, too too vain, diſcurres.</l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:199600:35"/>
                     <l>Mean be thy meaſure, elſe thy ſtrains are Slurres.</l>
                     <l>I want a ſervant yet: O there he ſtands;</l>
                     <l>'Tis he that ran deviſion beſt: 'Twas he</l>
                     <l>Which rounded, with a Crimſon twiſt of ſilk,</l>
                     <l>This neck with pretious Rubies once adorn'd.</l>
                     <l>But now more fulgent ſhines (with that he gave)</l>
                     <l>VVith all the ſplendours of Heaven's richer gemms.</l>
                     <l>Thanks for this favour Headſman. To forgive
<stage>Gives him Money in a Purſe.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVere ſmall requital. Here; believe and live.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Fair goddeſs of the Earth.
<stage>Kneeling.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art deceiv'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſm.</speaker>
                     <p>O! more than woman then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>That I deny.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Then faireſt Virgin, this hard heart of ſtone</l>
                     <l>Y'have mollified. Vouchſafe to take this ſword.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>Only to kiſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſ.</speaker>
                     <l>And cut off his right hand,</l>
                     <l>VVhich has tranſgreſs'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>O! do not tempt to ſin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Then I believe, there is a greater power</l>
                     <l>Of goodneſs in your ſoul, than all our gods.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <p>From one it is deriv'd who raigns above:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Headſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Him I confeſs; in him believe,—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>And love.</l>
                     <l>O my dear Parents can you then, not love</l>
                     <l>That power immortal? not believe in him,</l>
                     <l>VVhom he adores with me, a true Believer?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar. Fla.</speaker>
                     <p>VVe do, we do, with thee, to live and die.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>In Paradice in joy ſhall ever laſt:</l>
                     <l>Sound muſick then and let me ſing my laſt.</l>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Sings.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Glorious Sun thy beams diſplay</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To the dawning of this day.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That this payre who gave me being</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>May the light of truth be ſeeing.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Come dear Parents on each ſide,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lead me now who am your guide,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That you may who gave me being</hi>
                           <stage>The Song ended, horrid Muſick.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Live in bliſse, which is by ſeeing.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:199600:35"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>What hideous noyſe: what winde is this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>That which never blows to good. Behold 'tis he</l>
                     <l>Who lurking in the Idol's is ador'd.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter Devils leading</hi> Saphricius, <hi>with a Wreath of Serpents on his head:</hi> Almachius <hi>and Officers led in Chains:</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Leading a Renegade who has rejected</l>
                     <l>What you embrace: with him enchain'd the Judge</l>
                     <l>And Officers are led, his Vaſſals now.
<stage>Heavenly Muſick.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Angels and Bleſſed Spirits,</hi> Valerian, Tiburtius, Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Nicephorus; <hi>all with Crowns on their heads: the good goe out on the right hand, the bad on the left.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>My Childe what muſick's this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>As oppoſite</l>
                     <l>To what you heard, as is this glorious Wight</l>
                     <l>To that infernal monſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>And what are theſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cec.</speaker>
                     <l>Thrice Happy ſouls, that of <hi>Valerian,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This <hi>Tiburtius:</hi> the third of <hi>Maximus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhoſe candid Veſts with bloody tincture ſhine.</l>
                     <l>Laſtly that <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> who ſnatch'd a Crown</l>
                     <l>That was from Heaven deſcending on that head</l>
                     <l>VVhere now is ſeen à wreath of poyſoning ſerpents.</l>
                     <l>Come Parents follow theſe who lead the way</l>
                     <l>To endleſs happineſs: forſake that Night</l>
                     <l>And Fogg of Hell which never ſhall ſee light.
<stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Manent Attendentes</hi> Ceciliae, <hi>to ſpeak the</hi> EPILOGUE.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Hum! ha! hum!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Palinodio</hi> what doſt mean to doe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Uſher the Epilogue to th' Stage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phan.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou might'ſt,</l>
                     <l>VVere it a Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <l>Such I'le prove it is.</l>
                     <l>For as a Lady is cry'd up for fair</l>
                     <l>By one, by another but indifferent,</l>
                     <l>And not ſo much by a third, but infinitely</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:199600:36"/>
                     <l>Cry'd down; So are out Playes and Epilogues.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Metr.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet a good Speaker i'th Concluſion,</l>
                     <l>(Which thou art not) may crye it up agen,</l>
                     <l>Therefore give way to me <hi>Phantaſio.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pal.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, were the Prologue to be ſung, I would.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <p>Tuſh! how impertinent you are! am not I The Poet?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <l>What then? ſo was the Water-man,</l>
                     <l>Who puffing row'd his Prologue to the Stage</l>
                     <l>As he was won't to toyl 'gainſt tyde and winde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Away, you all contend but to no purpoſe,</l>
                     <l>Was not the ſubject of our Play a Lady?</l>
                     <l>Whom then but Ladies do's it moſt concern?</l>
                     <l>Or whom, if not one of her ſex, doth it</l>
                     <l>Beſeem to ſpeak the Epilogue?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pha.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true,</l>
                     <l>I grant for Ladies this ſutes well.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Then Poet</l>
                     <l>To men make your Addreſſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <p>I will, hum! ha! hum!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>More manners Sir, Ladies muſt firſt be ſerv'd. Ladies,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anguſta,</speaker>
                     <l>here (who would <hi>Auguſta</hi> ſhine</l>
                     <l>In Court like to your ſelves) loſt her deſign,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſtill ambitious to be happier now,</l>
                     <l>Courting the Female ſex, I need not bow</l>
                     <l>In a ſubmiſſive way; for that would bee</l>
                     <l>To wrong our Poet, who requeſted mee,</l>
                     <l>Only to tell you, cauſe you are cry'd down</l>
                     <l>As creatures of leſs merit, leſs renown)</l>
                     <l>To ſet before your eyes what your ſex can,</l>
                     <l>At leaſt as good if not excelling man.</l>
                     <l>As conſtant, firm, as reſolute in all;</l>
                     <l>As vertuous every way, now when you ſhall</l>
                     <l>Reflect upon the Maſter-piece you've ſeen,</l>
                     <l>(Applauding that) you needs muſt have within</l>
                     <l>A Candid breſt, (which fully ſhall requite</l>
                     <l>Our Authors labour) that we call delight,</l>
                     <l>VVhich uſhers Vertue unto higher ſtrayns.</l>
                     <l>You have his ſcope, to recompenſe his pains;</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:199600:36"/>
                     <l>But emulate his Copy,—I'th mean while</l>
                     <l>It is enough t'obtain a Lady's ſmile.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Met.</speaker>
                     <l>Gentlemen,</l>
                     <l>Sh' has ſaid enough, what then is left for me?</l>
                     <l>Onely t'entreat a quick Reflexion; ſee</l>
                     <l>And well obſerve each Ladies Eye and Look,</l>
                     <l>To ſympathize with them is but to brook</l>
                     <l>VVhat pleaſes them; — Ladies example give</l>
                     <l>By clear Aſpects whether we die or live:</l>
                     <l>For we conclude,—ſo ſails our Ship to day,</l>
                     <l>By Ladies we are ſav'd, or caſt away.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
